Today I'm excited to talk about bridging
Today I'm excited to talk about bridging informal and formal mathematical
informal and formal mathematical
informal and formal mathematical reasoning with
reasoning with
reasoning with AI.
AI.
AI. And so probably throughout this course
And so probably throughout this course
And so probably throughout this course um you've seen many different ways where
um you've seen many different ways where
um you've seen many different ways where these AI agents can start to have a lot
these AI agents can start to have a lot
these AI agents can start to have a lot of impact in different areas. And so one
of impact in different areas. And so one
of impact in different areas. And so one interesting question is to what extent
interesting question is to what extent
interesting question is to what extent can they impact more expert domains? So
can they impact more expert domains? So
can they impact more expert domains? So say finance, science, medicine. and the
say finance, science, medicine. and the
say finance, science, medicine. and the domain that I'll talk about today, which
domain that I'll talk about today, which
domain that I'll talk about today, which is
is
is mathematics. Now, with
mathematics. Now, with
mathematics. Now, with mathematics, there's a variety of things
mathematics, there's a variety of things
mathematics, there's a variety of things that you could imagine doing with an
that you could imagine doing with an
that you could imagine doing with an agent or a language model. You could try
agent or a language model. You could try
agent or a language model. You could try to have an open-ended dialogue with the
to have an open-ended dialogue with the
to have an open-ended dialogue with the model. You could try to have it come up
model. You could try to have it come up
model. You could try to have it come up with counter examples for you, help you
with counter examples for you, help you
with counter examples for you, help you write proofs, and it's your imagination
write proofs, and it's your imagination
write proofs, and it's your imagination is basically uh the limit.
is basically uh the limit.
is basically uh the limit. Um and what I want to argue today is
Um and what I want to argue today is
Um and what I want to argue today is that for math in particular, how you
that for math in particular, how you
that for math in particular, how you represent the math is actually extremely
represent the math is actually extremely
represent the math is actually extremely important to think
important to think
important to think about. So one way to represent math is
about. So one way to represent math is
about. So one way to represent math is what is called informal mathematics.
what is called informal mathematics.
what is called informal mathematics. Here math is represented as raw data. So
Here math is represented as raw data. So
Here math is represented as raw data. So it could be text, it could be an image,
it could be text, it could be an image,
it could be text, it could be an image, it could be even audio if you're like
it could be even audio if you're like
it could be even audio if you're like talking with someone about math. And
talking with someone about math. And
talking with someone about math. And doing this is extremely flexible. And in
doing this is extremely flexible. And in
doing this is extremely flexible. And in some sense, most of the math that you've
some sense, most of the math that you've
some sense, most of the math that you've encountered or that you've used is
encountered or that you've used is
encountered or that you've used is probably in some kind of informal
probably in some kind of informal
probably in some kind of informal format. So even something like a latex
format. So even something like a latex
format. So even something like a latex solution or an archive paper we would
solution or an archive paper we would
solution or an archive paper we would consider to be informal.
consider to be informal.
consider to be informal. Now when we think about using AI to
Now when we think about using AI to
Now when we think about using AI to generate or operate in informal math
generate or operate in informal math
generate or operate in informal math there is a really important problem
there is a really important problem
there is a really important problem which is that we don't have any
which is that we don't have any
which is that we don't have any guarantees that the math is correct or
guarantees that the math is correct or
guarantees that the math is correct or not. So like here is an example of a
not. So like here is an example of a
not. So like here is an example of a language model producing a solution and
language model producing a solution and
language model producing a solution and the answer at the end is actually
the answer at the end is actually
the answer at the end is actually correct but it makes these kind of
correct but it makes these kind of
correct but it makes these kind of subtle mistakes in the intermediate
subtle mistakes in the intermediate
subtle mistakes in the intermediate steps. And so for really simple math,
steps. And so for really simple math,
steps. And so for really simple math, this might not actually be an issue and
this might not actually be an issue and
this might not actually be an issue and the language model might still be
the language model might still be
the language model might still be useful. But if we really want to trust
useful. But if we really want to trust
useful. But if we really want to trust it in say education or in research level
it in say education or in research level
it in say education or in research level math, then it could get very
math, then it could get very
math, then it could get very tedious and very difficult to know
tedious and very difficult to know
tedious and very difficult to know whether the outputs are correct or
whether the outputs are correct or
whether the outputs are correct or not. So this motivates the other end of
not. So this motivates the other end of
not. So this motivates the other end of the spectrum which is called formal
the spectrum which is called formal
the spectrum which is called formal mathematics. Here math is written as
mathematics. Here math is written as
mathematics. Here math is written as source code in a programming language
source code in a programming language
source code in a programming language and basically the way it works is you
and basically the way it works is you
and basically the way it works is you can write a specification or a lema or
can write a specification or a lema or
can write a specification or a lema or theorem like 1 plus 1 equals 2 then you
theorem like 1 plus 1 equals 2 then you
theorem like 1 plus 1 equals 2 then you can write a proof and the really cool
can write a proof and the really cool
can write a proof and the really cool thing is that if all of the code
thing is that if all of the code
thing is that if all of the code compiles then you have a formal
compiles then you have a formal
compiles then you have a formal guarantee that the proof is
guarantee that the proof is
guarantee that the proof is correct. And so this is a lot different
correct. And so this is a lot different
correct. And so this is a lot different than the informal math because now we
than the informal math because now we
than the informal math because now we can have certainty if say a language
can have certainty if say a language
can have certainty if say a language model generates a proof that it is
model generates a proof that it is
model generates a proof that it is actually a reliable and correct proof of
actually a reliable and correct proof of
actually a reliable and correct proof of the
the
the theorem. And there's been a variety of
theorem. And there's been a variety of
theorem. And there's been a variety of these theorem proofing languages
these theorem proofing languages
these theorem proofing languages developed. I'll mostly focus on a
developed. I'll mostly focus on a
developed. I'll mostly focus on a language called lean which recently is
language called lean which recently is
language called lean which recently is having a really exciting uh really
having a really exciting uh really
having a really exciting uh really exciting growth and really exciting
exciting growth and really exciting
exciting growth and really exciting intersection with the mathematical
intersection with the mathematical
intersection with the mathematical community which I'll talk about in a
community which I'll talk about in a
community which I'll talk about in a bit. And for one of the topics that I'll
bit. And for one of the topics that I'll
bit. And for one of the topics that I'll talk about I'll also mention this
talk about I'll also mention this
talk about I'll also mention this language called Isabel because it has
language called Isabel because it has
language called Isabel because it has some features that make it kind of
some features that make it kind of
some features that make it kind of amendable to writing different types of
amendable to writing different types of
amendable to writing different types of proofs with AI systems.
proofs with AI systems.
proofs with AI systems. So if you haven't seen one of these
So if you haven't seen one of these
So if you haven't seen one of these before, um I wanted to actually show you
before, um I wanted to actually show you
before, um I wanted to actually show you what one of these formal proof
what one of these formal proof
what one of these formal proof assistants looked like. Um and so to do
assistants looked like. Um and so to do
assistants looked like. Um and so to do this, we'll try to prove this really
this, we'll try to prove this really
this, we'll try to prove this really simple theorem, uh which is like
simple theorem, uh which is like
simple theorem, uh which is like transitivity. So if R is a subset of S
transitivity. So if R is a subset of S
transitivity. So if R is a subset of S and S is a subset of T, then R is a
and S is a subset of T, then R is a
and S is a subset of T, then R is a subset of
subset of
subset of T. So um I'll actually show you this um
T. So um I'll actually show you this um
T. So um I'll actually show you this um as a demo. And so here what I've done is
as a demo. And so here what I've done is
as a demo. And so here what I've done is I've opened up VS code. And so as I
I've opened up VS code. And so as I
I've opened up VS code. And so as I mentioned this is literally um like
mentioned this is literally um like
mentioned this is literally um like programming like like writing code. And
programming like like writing code. And
programming like like writing code. And here you could see the theorem
here you could see the theorem
here you could see the theorem statement. Uh so if R is a subset of S
statement. Uh so if R is a subset of S
statement. Uh so if R is a subset of S and S is a subset of T then R is a
and S is a subset of T then R is a
and S is a subset of T then R is a subset of T.
subset of T.
subset of T. And these are often called interactive
And these are often called interactive
And these are often called interactive proof assistants because what happens is
proof assistants because what happens is
proof assistants because what happens is as I go to write a proof, it actually
as I go to write a proof, it actually
as I go to write a proof, it actually tells me over here what is the current
tells me over here what is the current
tells me over here what is the current state of the proof. So the idea isn't to
state of the proof. So the idea isn't to
state of the proof. So the idea isn't to learn every bit of the formal system,
learn every bit of the formal system,
learn every bit of the formal system, but I'm kind of just showing you the
but I'm kind of just showing you the
but I'm kind of just showing you the important parts that'll be relevant for
important parts that'll be relevant for
important parts that'll be relevant for the talk. So here we can see these
the talk. So here we can see these
the talk. So here we can see these different variables and we can see what
different variables and we can see what
different variables and we can see what we have uh remaining to prove over here.
we have uh remaining to prove over here.
we have uh remaining to prove over here. Now the thing is is that it takes some
Now the thing is is that it takes some
Now the thing is is that it takes some expertise to actually write a proof in
expertise to actually write a proof in
expertise to actually write a proof in lean. So for example if I know some lean
lean. So for example if I know some lean
lean. So for example if I know some lean then one thing I can do is this command
then one thing I can do is this command
then one thing I can do is this command here and you can notice that it actually
here and you can notice that it actually
here and you can notice that it actually changed the state of the proof. So now I
changed the state of the proof. So now I
changed the state of the proof. So now I have these two kind of variables up here
have these two kind of variables up here
have these two kind of variables up here and the goal has also changed.
and the goal has also changed.
and the goal has also changed. Then again if you have some expertise
Then again if you have some expertise
Then again if you have some expertise then you can actually know that this
then you can actually know that this
then you can actually know that this idea of
idea of
idea of transitivity has already been programmed
transitivity has already been programmed
transitivity has already been programmed uh into lean. So here I wrote this um
uh into lean. So here I wrote this um
uh into lean. So here I wrote this um transitivity um rule here or or lema and
transitivity um rule here or or lema and
transitivity um rule here or or lema and now you can see up here that it says
now you can see up here that it says
now you can see up here that it says that there's no goals left. So I've kind
that there's no goals left. So I've kind
that there's no goals left. So I've kind of completed the
of completed the
of completed the proof. So we'll actually touch on a lot
proof. So we'll actually touch on a lot
proof. So we'll actually touch on a lot of things that I've talked about here
of things that I've talked about here
of things that I've talked about here throughout the talk. We'll talk about
throughout the talk. We'll talk about
throughout the talk. We'll talk about the fact that it requires some expertise
the fact that it requires some expertise
the fact that it requires some expertise to actually write a proof in one of
to actually write a proof in one of
to actually write a proof in one of these proof
these proof
these proof assistants. And if you look at this
assistants. And if you look at this
assistants. And if you look at this proof, it might look a bit different
proof, it might look a bit different
proof, it might look a bit different than one that you would see like written
than one that you would see like written
than one that you would see like written down in a textbook or something like
down in a textbook or something like
down in a textbook or something like that. So we'll revisit these ideas uh
that. So we'll revisit these ideas uh
that. So we'll revisit these ideas uh throughout the talk.
throughout the talk.
throughout the talk. So now going back to the talk
So now going back to the talk
So now going back to the talk um we could ask like okay I showed you
um we could ask like okay I showed you
um we could ask like okay I showed you this very simple example but is this is
this very simple example but is this is
this very simple example but is this is this kind of toy or is this actually
this kind of toy or is this actually
this kind of toy or is this actually useful for more complex
useful for more complex
useful for more complex mathematics. So a really exciting thing
mathematics. So a really exciting thing
mathematics. So a really exciting thing is that increasingly there's a larger
is that increasingly there's a larger
is that increasingly there's a larger and larger intersection with the
and larger intersection with the
and larger intersection with the mathematical community. So here's an
mathematical community. So here's an
mathematical community. So here's an example of the mathematician Terrence
example of the mathematician Terrence
example of the mathematician Terrence Tao and he formalized in lean the proof
Tao and he formalized in lean the proof
Tao and he formalized in lean the proof of a theorem from one of his actual
of a theorem from one of his actual
of a theorem from one of his actual papers and a really exciting thing
papers and a really exciting thing
papers and a really exciting thing that's kind of playing into this is this
that's kind of playing into this is this
that's kind of playing into this is this project which is called math lab. So if
project which is called math lab. So if
project which is called math lab. So if you noticed in the demo I gave this idea
you noticed in the demo I gave this idea
you noticed in the demo I gave this idea of transitivity was already kind of
of transitivity was already kind of
of transitivity was already kind of programmed in and that's the idea of
programmed in and that's the idea of
programmed in and that's the idea of math lab. So lots of people are
math lab. So lots of people are
math lab. So lots of people are contributing and kind of building up
contributing and kind of building up
contributing and kind of building up foundations that other people can use to
foundations that other people can use to
foundations that other people can use to make it easier to write more and more uh
make it easier to write more and more uh
make it easier to write more and more uh complex
complex
complex math. And if you look at what
math. And if you look at what
math. And if you look at what mathematicians write or or talk to them
mathematicians write or or talk to them
mathematicians write or or talk to them and um listen to what they say then
and um listen to what they say then
and um listen to what they say then these formal proof assistants are
these formal proof assistants are
these formal proof assistants are exciting for a few different reasons. So
exciting for a few different reasons. So
exciting for a few different reasons. So one is that they can potentially enable
one is that they can potentially enable
one is that they can potentially enable a new form of
a new form of
a new form of collaboration. So what you can do is you
collaboration. So what you can do is you
collaboration. So what you can do is you can break down a kind of big problem or
can break down a kind of big problem or
can break down a kind of big problem or big proof into multiple
big proof into multiple
big proof into multiple pieces and then anyone can go on and
pieces and then anyone can go on and
pieces and then anyone can go on and essentially submit code to try to solve
essentially submit code to try to solve
essentially submit code to try to solve one of the pieces to say prove one of
one of the pieces to say prove one of
one of the pieces to say prove one of the kind of helper theorems or helper
the kind of helper theorems or helper
the kind of helper theorems or helper lemas. And then the cool thing is that
lemas. And then the cool thing is that
lemas. And then the cool thing is that we know for a fact that we can trust the
we know for a fact that we can trust the
we know for a fact that we can trust the code since lean will automatically check
code since lean will automatically check
code since lean will automatically check it. And so this is a lot different than
it. And so this is a lot different than
it. And so this is a lot different than the typical way of collaborating on say
the typical way of collaborating on say
the typical way of collaborating on say a math paper where you kind of have to
a math paper where you kind of have to
a math paper where you kind of have to trust the author or read through their
trust the author or read through their
trust the author or read through their uh
uh
uh results. It also gives you instant
results. It also gives you instant
results. It also gives you instant feedback as we saw. So this could be
feedback as we saw. So this could be
feedback as we saw. So this could be useful in a variety of ways including
useful in a variety of ways including
useful in a variety of ways including when trying to learn math and of course
when trying to learn math and of course
when trying to learn math and of course it has these guarantees on
it has these guarantees on
it has these guarantees on correctness. So hopefully I've convinced
correctness. So hopefully I've convinced
correctness. So hopefully I've convinced you that formal math is getting more and
you that formal math is getting more and
you that formal math is getting more and more interesting for learning or for the
more interesting for learning or for the
more interesting for learning or for the actual mathematical community. But why
actual mathematical community. But why
actual mathematical community. But why is it actually important for AI? Well,
is it actually important for AI? Well,
is it actually important for AI? Well, one thing is that as we all know, we are
one thing is that as we all know, we are
one thing is that as we all know, we are not able to automatically check or trust
not able to automatically check or trust
not able to automatically check or trust the outputs of AI models. And so what
the outputs of AI models. And so what
the outputs of AI models. And so what the formal system gives us is some way
the formal system gives us is some way
the formal system gives us is some way of just preventing incorrect math or it
of just preventing incorrect math or it
of just preventing incorrect math or it turns out you can actually use this for
turns out you can actually use this for
turns out you can actually use this for code as well.
code as well.
code as well. Increasingly, we see more and more
Increasingly, we see more and more
Increasingly, we see more and more models trained with reinforcement
models trained with reinforcement
models trained with reinforcement learning. And I'll actually talk about
learning. And I'll actually talk about
learning. And I'll actually talk about one of those in the talk. And what you
one of those in the talk. And what you
one of those in the talk. And what you can think of the formal system as being
can think of the formal system as being
can think of the formal system as being is it gives you this kind of perfect
is it gives you this kind of perfect
is it gives you this kind of perfect reward signal of whether something is
reward signal of whether something is
reward signal of whether something is correct or not correct. And this turns
correct or not correct. And this turns
correct or not correct. And this turns out to be very useful for then improving
out to be very useful for then improving
out to be very useful for then improving machine learning models further.
machine learning models further.
machine learning models further. It also gets at one of the hot topics in
It also gets at one of the hot topics in
It also gets at one of the hot topics in the field right now, which is reasoning.
the field right now, which is reasoning.
the field right now, which is reasoning. And it gives you this nice playground
And it gives you this nice playground
And it gives you this nice playground where you can try even very easy
where you can try even very easy
where you can try even very easy reasoning problems to essentially
reasoning problems to essentially
reasoning problems to essentially arbitrarily hard ones within the domain
arbitrarily hard ones within the domain
arbitrarily hard ones within the domain of math.
of math.
of math. And so if we look at the history of
And so if we look at the history of
And so if we look at the history of language models in formal math, one of
language models in formal math, one of
language models in formal math, one of the pioneering works happened in 2020
the pioneering works happened in 2020
the pioneering works happened in 2020 from these two authors from OpenAI and
from these two authors from OpenAI and
from these two authors from OpenAI and they developed a system called
they developed a system called
they developed a system called GPTF and so it actually used the
GPTF and so it actually used the
GPTF and so it actually used the language model to kind of predict the
language model to kind of predict the
language model to kind of predict the next steps of these
next steps of these
next steps of these proofs and even back then they got some
proofs and even back then they got some
proofs and even back then they got some pretty interesting results. So what they
pretty interesting results. So what they
pretty interesting results. So what they did is they had the system uh generate a
did is they had the system uh generate a
did is they had the system uh generate a proof and then they submitted it as a
proof and then they submitted it as a
proof and then they submitted it as a pull request and here are some of the
pull request and here are some of the
pull request and here are some of the comments from the kind of maintainers of
comments from the kind of maintainers of
comments from the kind of maintainers of the formal proof library. Um even this
the formal proof library. Um even this
the formal proof library. Um even this model back then could produce kind of
model back then could produce kind of
model back then could produce kind of shorter proofs and some of them were
shorter proofs and some of them were
shorter proofs and some of them were even philosophically uh more concise
even philosophically uh more concise
even philosophically uh more concise than the human written
than the human written
than the human written ones. And then since then we've seen
ones. And then since then we've seen
ones. And then since then we've seen rapid progress in using methods based on
rapid progress in using methods based on
rapid progress in using methods based on language models for formal theorem
language models for formal theorem
language models for formal theorem proving. So here is showing the
proving. So here is showing the
proving. So here is showing the performance on a really common
performance on a really common
performance on a really common benchmark. These are based on math
benchmark. These are based on math
benchmark. These are based on math competition problems. And I actually
competition problems. And I actually
competition problems. And I actually made this plot a few months ago but it's
made this plot a few months ago but it's
made this plot a few months ago but it's already out of date. Uh actually just
already out of date. Uh actually just
already out of date. Uh actually just this morning there was a model released
this morning there was a model released
this morning there was a model released that get like 80% on this benchmark.
that get like 80% on this benchmark.
that get like 80% on this benchmark. And just to give you some flavor of what
And just to give you some flavor of what
And just to give you some flavor of what these look like, again, you don't have
these look like, again, you don't have
these look like, again, you don't have to read through the details of this or
to read through the details of this or
to read through the details of this or through most of the examples I show in
through most of the examples I show in
through most of the examples I show in this talk, but here's an actual um
this talk, but here's an actual um
this talk, but here's an actual um output from a model called Deepseek
output from a model called Deepseek
output from a model called Deepseek Prover. And it managed to produce this
Prover. And it managed to produce this
Prover. And it managed to produce this proof of an IMO
proof of an IMO
proof of an IMO problem. And so hopefully it gives you
problem. And so hopefully it gives you
problem. And so hopefully it gives you some sense that the outputs of these are
some sense that the outputs of these are
some sense that the outputs of these are starting to get pretty non-trivial.
And Terrence Tao, if we go back to
And Terrence Tao, if we go back to members of the mathematical community,
members of the mathematical community,
members of the mathematical community, uh wrote that during his formalization
uh wrote that during his formalization
uh wrote that during his formalization project, he was actually using GitHub
project, he was actually using GitHub
project, he was actually using GitHub co-pilot and um sometimes was able to
co-pilot and um sometimes was able to
co-pilot and um sometimes was able to like infer the directions he was going
like infer the directions he was going
like infer the directions he was going on going in and things like that.
on going in and things like that.
on going in and things like that. So with all this with formal math being
So with all this with formal math being
So with all this with formal math being so exciting for both mathematics and for
so exciting for both mathematics and for
so exciting for both mathematics and for AI the question is why don't people in
AI the question is why don't people in
AI the question is why don't people in AI always use formal math? What is the
AI always use formal math? What is the
AI always use formal math? What is the kind of blocker to making this happen?
kind of blocker to making this happen?
kind of blocker to making this happen? So I want to argue that the key
So I want to argue that the key
So I want to argue that the key challenge is that there's this gap
challenge is that there's this gap
challenge is that there's this gap between how people are familiar with
between how people are familiar with
between how people are familiar with doing math and the actual formal system.
doing math and the actual formal system.
doing math and the actual formal system. In particular, there's just so many
In particular, there's just so many
In particular, there's just so many ideas and intuitions and even the way
ideas and intuitions and even the way
ideas and intuitions and even the way that we write proofs that are just
that we write proofs that are just
that we write proofs that are just difficult or very tedious to express in
difficult or very tedious to express in
difficult or very tedious to express in the formal system. In a formal system
the formal system. In a formal system
the formal system. In a formal system like lean, each step of reasoning needs
like lean, each step of reasoning needs
like lean, each step of reasoning needs to be explicitly spelled out in detail.
to be explicitly spelled out in detail.
to be explicitly spelled out in detail. And as we saw even in that very simple
And as we saw even in that very simple
And as we saw even in that very simple example that I gave, you often have to
example that I gave, you often have to
example that I gave, you often have to have a deep knowledge of the system like
have a deep knowledge of the system like
have a deep knowledge of the system like what things exist in the system and how
what things exist in the system and how
what things exist in the system and how to write the code and so
to write the code and so
to write the code and so on. And so the theme of this talk will
on. And so the theme of this talk will
on. And so the theme of this talk will be steps towards bridging the gap
be steps towards bridging the gap
be steps towards bridging the gap between informal reasoning and formal
between informal reasoning and formal
between informal reasoning and formal reasoning.
reasoning.
reasoning. Can we use AI and language models to get
Can we use AI and language models to get
Can we use AI and language models to get the best of both worlds? Maintain the
the best of both worlds? Maintain the
the best of both worlds? Maintain the flexibility of informal reasoning while
flexibility of informal reasoning while
flexibility of informal reasoning while having all of these benefits that I
having all of these benefits that I
having all of these benefits that I mentioned with operating in the formal
mentioned with operating in the formal
mentioned with operating in the formal system. And so I'll talk about three
system. And so I'll talk about three
system. And so I'll talk about three different directions that we and others
different directions that we and others
different directions that we and others in the community are
in the community are
in the community are pursuing. First I'll talk about
pursuing. First I'll talk about
pursuing. First I'll talk about incorporating informal thoughts into the
incorporating informal thoughts into the
incorporating informal thoughts into the formal theorem proving procedure.
formal theorem proving procedure.
formal theorem proving procedure. I'll talk about training models to think
I'll talk about training models to think
I'll talk about training models to think informally with reinforcement learning
informally with reinforcement learning
informally with reinforcement learning and in particular our recent work which
and in particular our recent work which
and in particular our recent work which is called lean
is called lean
is called lean star. Then I'll move to informal provers
star. Then I'll move to informal provers
star. Then I'll move to informal provers or informal proofs and I'll talk about
or informal proofs and I'll talk about
or informal proofs and I'll talk about how you can break down the problem of
how you can break down the problem of
how you can break down the problem of writing one of these proofs as first
writing one of these proofs as first
writing one of these proofs as first writing a sketch and then kind of
writing a sketch and then kind of
writing a sketch and then kind of filling in the lower level gaps of the
filling in the lower level gaps of the
filling in the lower level gaps of the sketch. So I'll talk about our work
sketch. So I'll talk about our work
sketch. So I'll talk about our work called draft sketch proof and then our
called draft sketch proof and then our
called draft sketch proof and then our recent work which is actually not even
recent work which is actually not even
recent work which is actually not even released yet of trying to enable tools
released yet of trying to enable tools
released yet of trying to enable tools that let you fill in the gaps of these
that let you fill in the gaps of these
that let you fill in the gaps of these sketches in the lean theorem
sketches in the lean theorem
sketches in the lean theorem prover and then finally at the end of
prover and then finally at the end of
prover and then finally at the end of the talk I will talk about more of a
the talk I will talk about more of a
the talk I will talk about more of a future direction that we are taking
future direction that we are taking
future direction that we are taking initial steps towards which is how do we
initial steps towards which is how do we
initial steps towards which is how do we actually make these systems useful to
actually make these systems useful to
actually make these systems useful to mathemat mathematicians doing research
mathemat mathematicians doing research
mathemat mathematicians doing research level
level
level mathematics. So in particular, I'll talk
mathematics. So in particular, I'll talk
mathematics. So in particular, I'll talk about one way in which the models could
about one way in which the models could
about one way in which the models could assist in these larger projects. I'll
assist in these larger projects. I'll
assist in these larger projects. I'll talk about some tools that actually
talk about some tools that actually
talk about some tools that actually already exist and you can try after the
already exist and you can try after the
already exist and you can try after the talk if you want and a new benchmark
talk if you want and a new benchmark
talk if you want and a new benchmark that tries to further progress of
that tries to further progress of
that tries to further progress of building these assistants for these
building these assistants for these
building these assistants for these complex research level type projects.
complex research level type projects.
complex research level type projects. So with that let me go to the first part
So with that let me go to the first part
So with that let me go to the first part where I will talk about uh integrating
where I will talk about uh integrating
where I will talk about uh integrating informal thoughts into formal theorem
informal thoughts into formal theorem
informal thoughts into formal theorem proving. So here this will largely be
proving. So here this will largely be
proving. So here this will largely be based on um our paper called leanar
based on um our paper called leanar
based on um our paper called leanar which we'll be presenting soon at
which we'll be presenting soon at
which we'll be presenting soon at iclear and here again we're in the
iclear and here again we're in the
iclear and here again we're in the setting of theorem proving uh in
setting of theorem proving uh in
setting of theorem proving uh in lean. So here we have the theorem that I
lean. So here we have the theorem that I
lean. So here we have the theorem that I showed you before at the top. And then
showed you before at the top. And then
showed you before at the top. And then as I showed you in the demo, you could
as I showed you in the demo, you could
as I showed you in the demo, you could think of this as a kind of interactive
think of this as a kind of interactive
think of this as a kind of interactive step-by-step process. So in particular,
step-by-step process. So in particular,
step-by-step process. So in particular, lean will give you this state of the
lean will give you this state of the
lean will give you this state of the proof and then one thing that you could
proof and then one thing that you could
proof and then one thing that you could do is you could send that state to a
do is you could send that state to a
do is you could send that state to a language model and it could try to
language model and it could try to
language model and it could try to generate the next step of the proof.
generate the next step of the proof.
generate the next step of the proof. Then you can provide the next step to
Then you can provide the next step to
Then you can provide the next step to lean and it can either tell you whether
lean and it can either tell you whether
lean and it can either tell you whether the proof is is done, whether there is
the proof is is done, whether there is
the proof is is done, whether there is an error or as we saw it can give you
an error or as we saw it can give you
an error or as we saw it can give you the next state of the
the next state of the
the next state of the proof. You could then continue this
proof. You could then continue this
proof. You could then continue this until you either give up or you reach a
until you either give up or you reach a
until you either give up or you reach a complete proof. And so in that sense,
complete proof. And so in that sense,
complete proof. And so in that sense, you can see one of these proofs as being
you can see one of these proofs as being
you can see one of these proofs as being a sequence of states and next steps or
a sequence of states and next steps or
a sequence of states and next steps or they're called tactics.
So in a bit more detail, what we want to
So in a bit more detail, what we want to do is train a model on some data set of
do is train a model on some data set of
do is train a model on some data set of inputs and outputs. So an example is you
inputs and outputs. So an example is you
inputs and outputs. So an example is you could have the model take in the proof
could have the model take in the proof
could have the model take in the proof state and output the next step. And what
state and output the next step. And what
state and output the next step. And what you typically do is you extract a lot of
you typically do is you extract a lot of
you typically do is you extract a lot of these state and next step examples from
these state and next step examples from
these state and next step examples from some corpus of theorems and proofs. So
some corpus of theorems and proofs. So
some corpus of theorems and proofs. So for example, you could use the entire
for example, you could use the entire
for example, you could use the entire math load project that I mentioned
math load project that I mentioned
math load project that I mentioned earlier or you could even have a model
earlier or you could even have a model
earlier or you could even have a model generate its own theorems and generate
generate its own theorems and generate
generate its own theorems and generate its own proofs and then ultimately you
its own proofs and then ultimately you
its own proofs and then ultimately you kind of turn it into a data
kind of turn it into a data
kind of turn it into a data set. Once you've trained a model, you
set. Once you've trained a model, you
set. Once you've trained a model, you then want to use it to generate full
then want to use it to generate full
then want to use it to generate full proofs. So the traditional way of doing
proofs. So the traditional way of doing
proofs. So the traditional way of doing this is through this kind of tree search
this is through this kind of tree search
this is through this kind of tree search procedure. Here's an example tree search
procedure. Here's an example tree search
procedure. Here's an example tree search called best first search. And basically
called best first search. And basically
called best first search. And basically the idea is you ask the model to
the idea is you ask the model to
the idea is you ask the model to generate multiple candidates for the
generate multiple candidates for the
generate multiple candidates for the next
next
next step. Then you somehow come up with a
step. Then you somehow come up with a
step. Then you somehow come up with a score for each one of these
score for each one of these
score for each one of these candidates. You choose the step with the
candidates. You choose the step with the
candidates. You choose the step with the highest score. So for instance, first we
highest score. So for instance, first we
highest score. So for instance, first we chose this uh intro H
chose this uh intro H
chose this uh intro H step. Then you can expand those further.
step. Then you can expand those further.
step. Then you can expand those further. choose the next highest scoring
choose the next highest scoring
choose the next highest scoring sequence. As you can see here, it kind
sequence. As you can see here, it kind
sequence. As you can see here, it kind of backtracked and then it took this
of backtracked and then it took this
of backtracked and then it took this green path which led to a correct
green path which led to a correct
green path which led to a correct proof. So this is just one possible
proof. So this is just one possible
proof. So this is just one possible strategy you could use for generating a
strategy you could use for generating a
strategy you could use for generating a full proof if your model can only
full proof if your model can only
full proof if your model can only predict the next step.
predict the next step.
predict the next step. So what we are interested in is can we
So what we are interested in is can we
So what we are interested in is can we go beyond just training the model on
go beyond just training the model on
go beyond just training the model on formal proofs and to generate formal
formal proofs and to generate formal
formal proofs and to generate formal proofs and instead train the model to
proofs and instead train the model to
proofs and instead train the model to think before each step of the formal
think before each step of the formal
think before each step of the formal proof. So in particular we want to train
proof. So in particular we want to train
proof. So in particular we want to train the model to generate what's on the
the model to generate what's on the
the model to generate what's on the right where before taking a step it
right where before taking a step it
right where before taking a step it outputs some reasoning and it's kind of
outputs some reasoning and it's kind of
outputs some reasoning and it's kind of free to decide whatever it wants to do
free to decide whatever it wants to do
free to decide whatever it wants to do with the reasoning. It could break down
with the reasoning. It could break down
with the reasoning. It could break down the problem. It could plan out the next
the problem. It could plan out the next
the problem. It could plan out the next step. It could even solve some
step. It could even solve some
step. It could even solve some computation that isn't really present in
computation that isn't really present in
computation that isn't really present in the formal
the formal
the formal proof. So why would you want to do this?
proof. So why would you want to do this?
proof. So why would you want to do this? Well, again, it could give the model
Well, again, it could give the model
Well, again, it could give the model some room to plan out what it is about
some room to plan out what it is about
some room to plan out what it is about to do. When you think about it, it can
to do. When you think about it, it can
to do. When you think about it, it can help diversify the search space since
help diversify the search space since
help diversify the search space since now the model is searching for proofs
now the model is searching for proofs
now the model is searching for proofs not just in the formal space but in the
not just in the formal space but in the
not just in the formal space but in the formal space augmented with these
formal space augmented with these
formal space augmented with these thoughts. And I won't go into details
thoughts. And I won't go into details
thoughts. And I won't go into details here, but there's been a lot of cool
here, but there's been a lot of cool
here, but there's been a lot of cool work in the language model community
work in the language model community
work in the language model community showing that adding in these kind of
showing that adding in these kind of
showing that adding in these kind of chain of thought in other domains can
chain of thought in other domains can
chain of thought in other domains can actually give a model which is more
actually give a model which is more
actually give a model which is more expressive in terms of the kinds of
expressive in terms of the kinds of
expressive in terms of the kinds of problems it can
problems it can
problems it can solve. So we have a few good reasons to
solve. So we have a few good reasons to
solve. So we have a few good reasons to try this out.
try this out.
try this out. Now the key issue here is that nowhere
Now the key issue here is that nowhere
Now the key issue here is that nowhere on the internet is there formal proofs
on the internet is there formal proofs
on the internet is there formal proofs written in lean that have these nice uh
written in lean that have these nice uh
written in lean that have these nice uh thoughts written out for them. And so
thoughts written out for them. And so
thoughts written out for them. And so what we have to do is actually design an
what we have to do is actually design an
what we have to do is actually design an algorithm so that a model kind of learns
algorithm so that a model kind of learns
algorithm so that a model kind of learns on its own to produce these thoughts
on its own to produce these thoughts
on its own to produce these thoughts that are useful for the proofs.
that are useful for the proofs.
that are useful for the proofs. So the algorithm is called lean star and
So the algorithm is called lean star and
So the algorithm is called lean star and it adopts this name from this other work
it adopts this name from this other work
it adopts this name from this other work called self-taught reasoner and the
called self-taught reasoner and the
called self-taught reasoner and the process basically has two different
process basically has two different
process basically has two different phases. Um so the highle idea is we want
phases. Um so the highle idea is we want
phases. Um so the highle idea is we want to learn to generate these thoughts via
to learn to generate these thoughts via
to learn to generate these thoughts via reinforcement learning. So first we have
reinforcement learning. So first we have
reinforcement learning. So first we have to initialize the model so that it can
to initialize the model so that it can
to initialize the model so that it can produce some type of thoughts and then
produce some type of thoughts and then
produce some type of thoughts and then we want to train it further so that it
we want to train it further so that it
we want to train it further so that it gets better at using the thoughts to
gets better at using the thoughts to
gets better at using the thoughts to prove theorems.
prove theorems.
prove theorems. So in the first step we use this kind of
So in the first step we use this kind of
So in the first step we use this kind of clever trick which is we can look at a
clever trick which is we can look at a
clever trick which is we can look at a state and the actual next step of the
state and the actual next step of the
state and the actual next step of the proof and then have a language model
proof and then have a language model
proof and then have a language model just
just
just retrospectively come up with some
retrospectively come up with some
retrospectively come up with some thought that describes the transition
thought that describes the transition
thought that describes the transition from the state to the next step. So what
from the state to the next step. So what
from the state to the next step. So what we found is that if you don't give this
we found is that if you don't give this
we found is that if you don't give this step then the language model might just
step then the language model might just
step then the language model might just output a kind of meaningless or
output a kind of meaningless or
output a kind of meaningless or incorrect thought but they were kind of
incorrect thought but they were kind of
incorrect thought but they were kind of good enough at coming up with some
good enough at coming up with some
good enough at coming up with some thought which described uh this
thought which described uh this
thought which described uh this transition. So then we can annotate a
transition. So then we can annotate a
transition. So then we can annotate a large set of proofs. So here for
large set of proofs. So here for
large set of proofs. So here for instance we take all of math lab and we
instance we take all of math lab and we
instance we take all of math lab and we can get like hundreds of thousands of
can get like hundreds of thousands of
can get like hundreds of thousands of examples of of state thought and next
examples of of state thought and next
examples of of state thought and next step. Then we can use that to train a
step. Then we can use that to train a
step. Then we can use that to train a model and it doesn't necessarily have to
model and it doesn't necessarily have to
model and it doesn't necessarily have to use um all 100,000 by the way for this
use um all 100,000 by the way for this
use um all 100,000 by the way for this initial step. You want to just train
initial step. You want to just train
initial step. You want to just train some initial model that knows to produce
some initial model that knows to produce
some initial model that knows to produce these thoughts um prior to taking steps.
these thoughts um prior to taking steps.
these thoughts um prior to taking steps. Then we want to take that model and put
Then we want to take that model and put
Then we want to take that model and put it into this loop. So we have the model
it into this loop. So we have the model
it into this loop. So we have the model generate full proofs. Then we ask lean
generate full proofs. Then we ask lean
generate full proofs. Then we ask lean to tell us whether they are correct or
to tell us whether they are correct or
to tell us whether they are correct or not. And then we use some type of
not. And then we use some type of
not. And then we use some type of reinforcement learning algorithm to
reinforcement learning algorithm to
reinforcement learning algorithm to improve the model
improve the model
improve the model further. So what we need is some method
further. So what we need is some method
further. So what we need is some method to generate proofs and we need to
to generate proofs and we need to
to generate proofs and we need to actually choose some algorithm to
actually choose some algorithm to
actually choose some algorithm to implement this with.
implement this with.
implement this with. So what we discovered is that this
So what we discovered is that this
So what we discovered is that this commonly used way of using the tree
commonly used way of using the tree
commonly used way of using the tree search or best for search was actually
search or best for search was actually
search or best for search was actually difficult to get to work when we added
difficult to get to work when we added
difficult to get to work when we added in these thoughts. I think one reason is
in these thoughts. I think one reason is
in these thoughts. I think one reason is that it gets difficult to actually
that it gets difficult to actually
that it gets difficult to actually assign a really good score to the
assign a really good score to the
assign a really good score to the thought and so as a result the tree
thought and so as a result the tree
thought and so as a result the tree search kind of didn't work um as well.
search kind of didn't work um as well.
search kind of didn't work um as well. So what we did is design a new method
So what we did is design a new method
So what we did is design a new method which is this kind of simple idea of
which is this kind of simple idea of
which is this kind of simple idea of generating multiple proofs in parallel.
generating multiple proofs in parallel.
generating multiple proofs in parallel. So for a given trajectory you kind of
So for a given trajectory you kind of
So for a given trajectory you kind of generate a step. If you get an error
generate a step. If you get an error
generate a step. If you get an error from lean you just retry on that same
from lean you just retry on that same
from lean you just retry on that same path and then you keep going up to a
path and then you keep going up to a
path and then you keep going up to a maximum number of steps or if you reach
maximum number of steps or if you reach
maximum number of steps or if you reach a you stop if you reach a complete
a you stop if you reach a complete
a you stop if you reach a complete proof.
Then for the algorithm we actually just
Then for the algorithm we actually just used the simplest possible algorithm.
used the simplest possible algorithm.
used the simplest possible algorithm. And so we as well as other groups are
And so we as well as other groups are
And so we as well as other groups are now exploring more um better
now exploring more um better
now exploring more um better reinforcement learning algorithms like
reinforcement learning algorithms like
reinforcement learning algorithms like online algorithms. Um but here we did
online algorithms. Um but here we did
online algorithms. Um but here we did something very simple which is you just
something very simple which is you just
something very simple which is you just collect the successful trajectories you
collect the successful trajectories you
collect the successful trajectories you add those to your data set and then you
add those to your data set and then you
add those to your data set and then you train a new model um on this data set of
train a new model um on this data set of
train a new model um on this data set of states thoughts and
states thoughts and
states thoughts and tactics. So this algorithm goes by
tactics. So this algorithm goes by
tactics. So this algorithm goes by various names. It's called expert
various names. It's called expert
various names. It's called expert iteration. It's also called restdm. It's
iteration. It's also called restdm. It's
iteration. It's also called restdm. It's also called rejection fine-tuning. But
also called rejection fine-tuning. But
also called rejection fine-tuning. But the idea is very simple.
the idea is very simple.
the idea is very simple. So then typically the way that these
So then typically the way that these
So then typically the way that these models are evaluated is on these math
models are evaluated is on these math
models are evaluated is on these math competition
competition
competition problems. So although we train the model
problems. So although we train the model
problems. So although we train the model on math lab, um here's a common test
on math lab, um here's a common test
on math lab, um here's a common test data set which is used which is called
data set which is used which is called
data set which is used which is called mini F2F. And here's an example problem
mini F2F. And here's an example problem
mini F2F. And here's an example problem from the international math
from the international math
from the international math olympiad. So here I've shown the
olympiad. So here I've shown the
olympiad. So here I've shown the informal version just to show you what
informal version just to show you what
informal version just to show you what the problem is like. But then the model
the problem is like. But then the model
the problem is like. But then the model here only gets the formal version and
here only gets the formal version and
here only gets the formal version and has to produce a
proof. So here are some results with an
proof. So here are some results with an early model that we tried in the
early model that we tried in the
early model that we tried in the project. So in red you can see the model
project. So in red you can see the model
project. So in red you can see the model that we started with and then in black
that we started with and then in black
that we started with and then in black you could see the model after we perform
you could see the model after we perform
you could see the model after we perform this initialization
this initialization
this initialization step. Then in gray we can see the model
step. Then in gray we can see the model
step. Then in gray we can see the model after we perform the expert iteration.
after we perform the expert iteration.
after we perform the expert iteration. And you can see that the lean star
And you can see that the lean star
And you can see that the lean star process basically took it from being
process basically took it from being
process basically took it from being worse than this baseline model which was
worse than this baseline model which was
worse than this baseline model which was based on this GPT4 agent to being better
based on this GPT4 agent to being better
based on this GPT4 agent to being better than
than
than it. Then at the end of the project we
it. Then at the end of the project we
it. Then at the end of the project we applied lean star to the best available
applied lean star to the best available
applied lean star to the best available base model at the time for theme
base model at the time for theme
base model at the time for theme proving. And again we saw these
proving. And again we saw these
proving. And again we saw these improvements um going from gray to
improvements um going from gray to
improvements um going from gray to black. And at the time that we did this,
black. And at the time that we did this,
black. And at the time that we did this, this was the kind of state-of-the-art
this was the kind of state-of-the-art
this was the kind of state-of-the-art for this mini F2F data
set. One really interesting thing is
set. One really interesting thing is that we found that models with the
that we found that models with the
that we found that models with the thoughts benefit more from scaling up
thoughts benefit more from scaling up
thoughts benefit more from scaling up the search budget or the kind of
the search budget or the kind of
the search budget or the kind of inference budget. So here we're seeing
inference budget. So here we're seeing
inference budget. So here we're seeing as we sample more and more steps either
as we sample more and more steps either
as we sample more and more steps either with our sampling method or as a
with our sampling method or as a
with our sampling method or as a baseline with the best first search how
baseline with the best first search how
baseline with the best first search how the performance uh looks and you can see
the performance uh looks and you can see
the performance uh looks and you can see that the gains we get from the green
that the gains we get from the green
that the gains we get from the green line which is lean star with the
line which is lean star with the
line which is lean star with the thoughts are more pronounced than the
thoughts are more pronounced than the
thoughts are more pronounced than the model that doesn't have the
model that doesn't have the
model that doesn't have the thoughts. And so this might be
thoughts. And so this might be
thoughts. And so this might be indicating the idea that I mentioned
indicating the idea that I mentioned
indicating the idea that I mentioned before that adding in these thoughts
before that adding in these thoughts
before that adding in these thoughts helps to kind of diversify the search
helps to kind of diversify the search
helps to kind of diversify the search space. Here's some examples. And again,
space. Here's some examples. And again,
space. Here's some examples. And again, you don't have to read through the
you don't have to read through the
you don't have to read through the details, but if you're curious, you can
details, but if you're curious, you can
details, but if you're curious, you can take a look at the paper after. One
take a look at the paper after. One
take a look at the paper after. One interesting thing here is that if you
interesting thing here is that if you
interesting thing here is that if you look at the formal code, there's
look at the formal code, there's
look at the formal code, there's actually some steps of reasoning that
actually some steps of reasoning that
actually some steps of reasoning that the model is doing in the informal
the model is doing in the informal
the model is doing in the informal thought shown in gray that aren't really
thought shown in gray that aren't really
thought shown in gray that aren't really present in the formal code.
present in the formal code.
present in the formal code. And here's a longer example, partly
And here's a longer example, partly
And here's a longer example, partly because it looks impressive, but also to
because it looks impressive, but also to
because it looks impressive, but also to just show you that when you add in these
just show you that when you add in these
just show you that when you add in these informal thoughts with the formal ones,
informal thoughts with the formal ones,
informal thoughts with the formal ones, um the output starts to get um yeah,
um the output starts to get um yeah,
um the output starts to get um yeah, fairly non-trivial.
So after lean star the really exciting
So after lean star the really exciting thing is that this idea of augmenting
thing is that this idea of augmenting
thing is that this idea of augmenting models or reasoning models with thoughts
models or reasoning models with thoughts
models or reasoning models with thoughts and training them with reinforcement
and training them with reinforcement
and training them with reinforcement learning um has been adopted in the
learning um has been adopted in the
learning um has been adopted in the theorem proving community. So in
theorem proving community. So in
theorem proving community. So in particular uh very rapidly this idea of
particular uh very rapidly this idea of
particular uh very rapidly this idea of incorporating thoughts became a part of
incorporating thoughts became a part of
incorporating thoughts became a part of the state-of-the-art systems. So here's
the state-of-the-art systems. So here's
the state-of-the-art systems. So here's the example that I mentioned before uh
the example that I mentioned before uh
the example that I mentioned before uh called deepseek prover where they
called deepseek prover where they
called deepseek prover where they incorporate in the informal thoughts and
incorporate in the informal thoughts and
incorporate in the informal thoughts and then as I mentioned just this morning
then as I mentioned just this morning
then as I mentioned just this morning there was this state-of-the-art prover
there was this state-of-the-art prover
there was this state-of-the-art prover released by um this uh startup and you
released by um this uh startup and you
released by um this uh startup and you can see that they have this idea of kind
can see that they have this idea of kind
can see that they have this idea of kind of alternating between informal
of alternating between informal
of alternating between informal reasoning and snippets of
reasoning and snippets of
reasoning and snippets of code and then more broadly these
code and then more broadly these
code and then more broadly these reasoning models that generate long
reasoning models that generate long
reasoning models that generate long chains of thought and are trained with
chains of thought and are trained with
chains of thought and are trained with reinforcement learning have really begun
reinforcement learning have really begun
reinforcement learning have really begun to revolutionize the LM LLM reasoning.
to revolutionize the LM LLM reasoning.
to revolutionize the LM LLM reasoning. So I'm not going to go into the details
So I'm not going to go into the details
So I'm not going to go into the details here, but you have probably heard of
here, but you have probably heard of
here, but you have probably heard of these models like OpenAI 01 and Deepseek
these models like OpenAI 01 and Deepseek
these models like OpenAI 01 and Deepseek R1. And so it seems like at least
R1. And so it seems like at least
R1. And so it seems like at least currently having this kind of informal
currently having this kind of informal
currently having this kind of informal thinking is a really key part of the
thinking is a really key part of the
thinking is a really key part of the reasoning
procedure. So to recap, Leanar kind of
procedure. So to recap, Leanar kind of builds on this observation that training
builds on this observation that training
builds on this observation that training only on the formal code may be
only on the formal code may be
only on the formal code may be insufficient to learn the actual thought
insufficient to learn the actual thought
insufficient to learn the actual thought process that's needed to produce the
process that's needed to produce the
process that's needed to produce the code. and it gives a kind of simple
code. and it gives a kind of simple
code. and it gives a kind of simple algorithm for learning to generate the
algorithm for learning to generate the
algorithm for learning to generate the thoughts. Now I'll move from informal
thoughts. Now I'll move from informal
thoughts. Now I'll move from informal thoughts to informal provers and
thoughts to informal provers and
thoughts to informal provers and informal proofs and in particular talk
informal proofs and in particular talk
informal proofs and in particular talk about methods that prove theorems by
about methods that prove theorems by
about methods that prove theorems by kind of producing this highle sketch and
kind of producing this highle sketch and
kind of producing this highle sketch and then filling in the gaps of the sketch.
So here the motivation is to combine the
So here the motivation is to combine the benefits of kind of higher level
benefits of kind of higher level
benefits of kind of higher level reasoning and lower level
reasoning and lower level
reasoning and lower level reasoning. And one motivation for this
reasoning. And one motivation for this
reasoning. And one motivation for this is to think about like how do we
is to think about like how do we
is to think about like how do we actually write one of these formal
actually write one of these formal
actually write one of these formal proofs in the formal proof assistant uh
proofs in the formal proof assistant uh
proofs in the formal proof assistant uh sorry informal proofs in the formal
sorry informal proofs in the formal
sorry informal proofs in the formal proof assistant.
proof assistant.
proof assistant. So again, you don't have to worry too
So again, you don't have to worry too
So again, you don't have to worry too much about the details of of this, but
much about the details of of this, but
much about the details of of this, but here we're trying to prove the statement
here we're trying to prove the statement
here we're trying to prove the statement on the left. And what is notable here is
on the left. And what is notable here is
on the left. And what is notable here is that we can somewhat break this informal
that we can somewhat break this informal
that we can somewhat break this informal proof up into these three different
proof up into these three different
proof up into these three different parts. Then it turns out that we can
parts. Then it turns out that we can
parts. Then it turns out that we can write this in the formal system using
write this in the formal system using
write this in the formal system using something that is structured kind of
something that is structured kind of
something that is structured kind of analogously to the informal proof. So
analogously to the informal proof. So
analogously to the informal proof. So this is a system called Isabel and it
this is a system called Isabel and it
this is a system called Isabel and it has this style where you can write these
has this style where you can write these
has this style where you can write these kind of intermediate claims or
kind of intermediate claims or
kind of intermediate claims or conjectures and if you look at it they
conjectures and if you look at it they
conjectures and if you look at it they somewhat line up with the different
somewhat line up with the different
somewhat line up with the different steps like here you have 10 * 280
steps like here you have 10 * 280
steps like here you have 10 * 280 divided by 40 which shows up here and
divided by 40 which shows up here and
divided by 40 which shows up here and then this is a way of basically writing
then this is a way of basically writing
then this is a way of basically writing okay let's complete the proof.
okay let's complete the proof.
okay let's complete the proof. Now the interesting thing here is that
Now the interesting thing here is that
Now the interesting thing here is that you still need to produce a proof of one
you still need to produce a proof of one
you still need to produce a proof of one of the of each one of these kind of
of the of each one of these kind of
of the of each one of these kind of higher level steps. So that is shown in
higher level steps. So that is shown in
higher level steps. So that is shown in green. And so you can see here that to
green. And so you can see here that to
green. And so you can see here that to actually come up with that proof, it
actually come up with that proof, it
actually come up with that proof, it doesn't really look like natural
doesn't really look like natural
doesn't really look like natural languages at all. Here it's actually
languages at all. Here it's actually
languages at all. Here it's actually calling this SMT solver and feeding it
calling this SMT solver and feeding it
calling this SMT solver and feeding it some facts.
some facts.
some facts. So interestingly we have this kind of
So interestingly we have this kind of
So interestingly we have this kind of decomposition between high level and
decomposition between high level and
decomposition between high level and these kind of lower level
these kind of lower level
these kind of lower level things. So let me actually say a bit
things. So let me actually say a bit
things. So let me actually say a bit more about how you produce these lower
more about how you produce these lower
more about how you produce these lower level proofs uh in a system like
level proofs uh in a system like
level proofs uh in a system like Isabel. So it turns out that there are
Isabel. So it turns out that there are
Isabel. So it turns out that there are these very powerful and very useful
these very powerful and very useful
these very powerful and very useful automation tools called hammers or this
automation tools called hammers or this
automation tools called hammers or this one is called sledgehammer.
one is called sledgehammer.
one is called sledgehammer. And the basic idea is that as you're
And the basic idea is that as you're
And the basic idea is that as you're writing a proof as you know a human, you
writing a proof as you know a human, you
writing a proof as you know a human, you could write one of these uh conjectures
could write one of these uh conjectures
could write one of these uh conjectures and then you could call the
and then you could call the
and then you could call the sledgehammer. What it does under the
sledgehammer. What it does under the
sledgehammer. What it does under the covers is it calls out to external
covers is it calls out to external
covers is it calls out to external automated provers, ones that are based
automated provers, ones that are based
automated provers, ones that are based on first order logic or higher order
on first order logic or higher order
on first order logic or higher order logic or SMT solvers.
logic or SMT solvers.
logic or SMT solvers. And these turn out to be extremely
And these turn out to be extremely
And these turn out to be extremely effective when you're using the system
effective when you're using the system
effective when you're using the system for kind of yeah filling in these little
for kind of yeah filling in these little
for kind of yeah filling in these little gaps of the
gaps of the
gaps of the proof. What these are not good at is
proof. What these are not good at is
proof. What these are not good at is let's say you want to solve an IMO
let's say you want to solve an IMO
let's say you want to solve an IMO problem. Then the sledgehammer methods
problem. Then the sledgehammer methods
problem. Then the sledgehammer methods just won't
just won't
just won't succeed. The technical reason is that
succeed. The technical reason is that
succeed. The technical reason is that based on how they're set up there is
based on how they're set up there is
based on how they're set up there is just such a large search space of
just such a large search space of
just such a large search space of possible proofs.
possible proofs.
possible proofs. And in particular, if you think about
And in particular, if you think about
And in particular, if you think about this proof as being structured as like
this proof as being structured as like
this proof as being structured as like these have statements, they don't really
these have statements, they don't really
these have statements, they don't really have the functionality to produce
have the functionality to produce
have the functionality to produce statements like that. So in practice,
statements like that. So in practice,
statements like that. So in practice, these are used kind of interactively as
these are used kind of interactively as
these are used kind of interactively as you're writing a proof as a
you're writing a proof as a
you're writing a proof as a human. So here the idea is we want to
human. So here the idea is we want to
human. So here the idea is we want to combine some kind of highle prover with
combine some kind of highle prover with
combine some kind of highle prover with a lower level prover like the
a lower level prover like the
a lower level prover like the sledgehammer.
sledgehammer.
sledgehammer. And this leads to our method which is
And this leads to our method which is
And this leads to our method which is called draft sketch proof which we
called draft sketch proof which we
called draft sketch proof which we presented in iClar in 2023 and uh
presented in iClar in 2023 and uh
presented in iClar in 2023 and uh developed and released in late uh
developed and released in late uh
developed and released in late uh 2022. So here the idea is to come up
2022. So here the idea is to come up
2022. So here the idea is to come up with this kind of three-step procedure.
with this kind of three-step procedure.
with this kind of three-step procedure. First we're going to draft an informal
First we're going to draft an informal
First we're going to draft an informal proof. Then we're going to translate it
proof. Then we're going to translate it
proof. Then we're going to translate it into this formal sketch. And then we're
into this formal sketch. And then we're
into this formal sketch. And then we're going to use a low-level prover to fill
going to use a low-level prover to fill
going to use a low-level prover to fill in the gaps of the
in the gaps of the
in the gaps of the sketch. So to show you this in more
sketch. So to show you this in more
sketch. So to show you this in more detail, let's walk through each one of
detail, let's walk through each one of
detail, let's walk through each one of these. So first we start off um with an
these. So first we start off um with an
these. So first we start off um with an informal theorem and a formal theorem
informal theorem and a formal theorem
informal theorem and a formal theorem statement. It's actually really
statement. It's actually really
statement. It's actually really important to provide the system with the
important to provide the system with the
important to provide the system with the formal theorem statement because when we
formal theorem statement because when we
formal theorem statement because when we start to translate things, uh we want to
start to translate things, uh we want to
start to translate things, uh we want to make sure that the model's not cheating
make sure that the model's not cheating
make sure that the model's not cheating and it's actually
and it's actually
and it's actually uh proving the thing that we wanted to
uh proving the thing that we wanted to
uh proving the thing that we wanted to prove. Then in the first step we have
prove. Then in the first step we have
prove. Then in the first step we have the system so it could be a human or it
the system so it could be a human or it
the system so it could be a human or it could be an LLM generate some informal
could be an LLM generate some informal
could be an LLM generate some informal proof. Then in the next step we have an
proof. Then in the next step we have an
proof. Then in the next step we have an LLM translate the informal proof into
LLM translate the informal proof into
LLM translate the informal proof into what's called a formal sketch. It's
what's called a formal sketch. It's
what's called a formal sketch. It's essentially what I showed you before
essentially what I showed you before
essentially what I showed you before except now we leave these gaps to be
except now we leave these gaps to be
except now we leave these gaps to be filled which are the lower level
filled which are the lower level
filled which are the lower level proofs. Then in the final stage we try
proofs. Then in the final stage we try
proofs. Then in the final stage we try to close the gap with a lower level
to close the gap with a lower level
to close the gap with a lower level prover. Here we are actually using the
prover. Here we are actually using the
prover. Here we are actually using the sledgehammer tool that I told you about.
sledgehammer tool that I told you about.
sledgehammer tool that I told you about. And if you're able to close all of the
And if you're able to close all of the
And if you're able to close all of the gaps then you're guaranteed to have a
gaps then you're guaranteed to have a
gaps then you're guaranteed to have a complete proof.
The interesting thing is that this
The interesting thing is that this actually looks a lot different than what
actually looks a lot different than what
actually looks a lot different than what I was showing you before where we have
I was showing you before where we have
I was showing you before where we have this kind of step-by-step proof search
this kind of step-by-step proof search
this kind of step-by-step proof search and maybe it's like a tree search. Now
and maybe it's like a tree search. Now
and maybe it's like a tree search. Now what we can do is we can diversify the
what we can do is we can diversify the
what we can do is we can diversify the search space by just generating many
search space by just generating many
search space by just generating many possible informal proofs or
possible informal proofs or
possible informal proofs or drafts and or generate many potential
drafts and or generate many potential
drafts and or generate many potential translations of those into formal
translations of those into formal
translations of those into formal sketches and then we can just try to
sketches and then we can just try to
sketches and then we can just try to fill in the gaps. And if the gaps are
fill in the gaps. And if the gaps are
fill in the gaps. And if the gaps are filled in any of the sketch sketches,
filled in any of the sketch sketches,
filled in any of the sketch sketches, then we have a formal proof that we
then we have a formal proof that we
then we have a formal proof that we could consider as the output of the
system. So here's showing what happens
system. So here's showing what happens as we scale up the number of calls to
as we scale up the number of calls to
as we scale up the number of calls to the pipeline. So here we're either
the pipeline. So here we're either
the pipeline. So here we're either generating many informal proof drafts or
generating many informal proof drafts or
generating many informal proof drafts or in the case of using a human written
in the case of using a human written
in the case of using a human written informal proof we're generating many
informal proof we're generating many
informal proof we're generating many possible translations into the formal
possible translations into the formal
possible translations into the formal sketch.
sketch.
sketch. You could see on the left hand side that
You could see on the left hand side that
You could see on the left hand side that if we just call the system once then it
if we just call the system once then it
if we just call the system once then it actually I mean it proves some things
actually I mean it proves some things
actually I mean it proves some things but it's not very good and we really see
but it's not very good and we really see
but it's not very good and we really see the benefits as we scale up the amount
the benefits as we scale up the amount
the benefits as we scale up the amount of proof search or sampling and up here
of proof search or sampling and up here
of proof search or sampling and up here we're proving a large number of
we're proving a large number of
we're proving a large number of problems. This is on the same mini FTF
problems. This is on the same mini FTF
problems. This is on the same mini FTF data
data
data set. Now this was in the days of codeex
set. Now this was in the days of codeex
set. Now this was in the days of codeex and manurva if you remember those
and manurva if you remember those
and manurva if you remember those models. And interestingly here if you
models. And interestingly here if you
models. And interestingly here if you look on the very right hand side if we
look on the very right hand side if we
look on the very right hand side if we actually sampled enough from the model
actually sampled enough from the model
actually sampled enough from the model then we were able to right at the end
then we were able to right at the end
then we were able to right at the end surpass the performance of using a human
surpass the performance of using a human
surpass the performance of using a human written proof. And so this was kind of
written proof. And so this was kind of
written proof. And so this was kind of exciting and probably now that language
exciting and probably now that language
exciting and probably now that language models are much better we would be able
models are much better we would be able
models are much better we would be able to um make that transition uh even
to um make that transition uh even
to um make that transition uh even earlier.
earlier.
earlier. So here's an example of proving an
So here's an example of proving an
So here's an example of proving an international math Olympia problem. So
international math Olympia problem. So
international math Olympia problem. So here the language model produces the
here the language model produces the
here the language model produces the informal proof shown in green. Then the
informal proof shown in green. Then the
informal proof shown in green. Then the language model produces the formal
language model produces the formal
language model produces the formal sketch shown in blue. You can see that
sketch shown in blue. You can see that
sketch shown in blue. You can see that here we actually um back then even had
here we actually um back then even had
here we actually um back then even had these informal kind of thoughts in as
these informal kind of thoughts in as
these informal kind of thoughts in as comments. Um or here it's show showing
comments. Um or here it's show showing
comments. Um or here it's show showing the informal version of the
the informal version of the
the informal version of the step. Um, and then we have the
step. Um, and then we have the
step. Um, and then we have the sledgehammer system fill in the gaps
sledgehammer system fill in the gaps
sledgehammer system fill in the gaps shown in purple. And you can see that
shown in purple. And you can see that
shown in purple. And you can see that sometimes it's pretty non-trivial. Like
sometimes it's pretty non-trivial. Like
sometimes it's pretty non-trivial. Like here again, it's calling this SMT solver
here again, it's calling this SMT solver
here again, it's calling this SMT solver and feeding in a bunch of different, uh,
and feeding in a bunch of different, uh,
and feeding in a bunch of different, uh, facts or
premises. So since then, um, I've put
premises. So since then, um, I've put together a tutorial for, um, theorem
together a tutorial for, um, theorem
together a tutorial for, um, theorem proving. So, it goes over the kind of
proving. So, it goes over the kind of
proving. So, it goes over the kind of step-by-step methods that I mentioned in
step-by-step methods that I mentioned in
step-by-step methods that I mentioned in the first part and also has a notebook
the first part and also has a notebook
the first part and also has a notebook that shows you how to implement this
that shows you how to implement this
that shows you how to implement this draft sketch proof method. And in
draft sketch proof method. And in
draft sketch proof method. And in particular, it just calls out to a
particular, it just calls out to a
particular, it just calls out to a language model API. So, you can try it
language model API. So, you can try it
language model API. So, you can try it out with one of the any state-of-the-art
out with one of the any state-of-the-art
out with one of the any state-of-the-art model uh that you want to if you're
model uh that you want to if you're
model uh that you want to if you're curious to to learn more.
So to recap, I talked about this method
So to recap, I talked about this method called draft sketch proof which
called draft sketch proof which
called draft sketch proof which generates these highle sketches and then
generates these highle sketches and then
generates these highle sketches and then tries to fill in the gaps. And what this
tries to fill in the gaps. And what this
tries to fill in the gaps. And what this relied on is in this language Isabel
relied on is in this language Isabel
relied on is in this language Isabel having this lower level prover called
having this lower level prover called
having this lower level prover called sledgehammer. So next I'm going to talk
sledgehammer. So next I'm going to talk
sledgehammer. So next I'm going to talk about our very recent work on trying to
about our very recent work on trying to
about our very recent work on trying to build one of these sledgehammer uh
build one of these sledgehammer uh
build one of these sledgehammer uh provers for lean so that we can more
provers for lean so that we can more
provers for lean so that we can more easily write these kind of sketchbased
easily write these kind of sketchbased
easily write these kind of sketchbased uh proofs in
uh proofs in
uh proofs in lean. So this is based on a paper that
lean. So this is based on a paper that
lean. So this is based on a paper that is um uh still not public which is
is um uh still not public which is
is um uh still not public which is called premise selection for a lean
called premise selection for a lean
called premise selection for a lean hammer where we build a system called
hammer where we build a system called
hammer where we build a system called lean hammer.
lean hammer.
lean hammer. So what is a hammer? So a hammer
So what is a hammer? So a hammer
So what is a hammer? So a hammer integrates as I mentioned these external
integrates as I mentioned these external
integrates as I mentioned these external provers and there's a bit of terminology
provers and there's a bit of terminology
provers and there's a bit of terminology here that is a bit tricky if you haven't
here that is a bit tricky if you haven't
here that is a bit tricky if you haven't seen the distinction before. Um
seen the distinction before. Um
seen the distinction before. Um specifically what it does is it
specifically what it does is it
specifically what it does is it integrates an automated theorem prover
integrates an automated theorem prover
integrates an automated theorem prover into an interactive theorem
into an interactive theorem
into an interactive theorem prover. So an interactive theorem prover
prover. So an interactive theorem prover
prover. So an interactive theorem prover is the like the one I showed you like
is the like the one I showed you like
is the like the one I showed you like lean and and essentially it's a
lean and and essentially it's a
lean and and essentially it's a programming language that is able to
programming language that is able to
programming language that is able to check the
check the
check the proofs. However, the language on its own
proofs. However, the language on its own
proofs. However, the language on its own doesn't give you a way of automatically
doesn't give you a way of automatically
doesn't give you a way of automatically producing the proofs. You usually have
producing the proofs. You usually have
producing the proofs. You usually have to write them as a human.
to write them as a human.
to write them as a human. An automated theorem prover is something
An automated theorem prover is something
An automated theorem prover is something that tries to automatically find proofs
that tries to automatically find proofs
that tries to automatically find proofs and traditionally these are based on
and traditionally these are based on
and traditionally these are based on different kinds of logics. So they might
different kinds of logics. So they might
different kinds of logics. So they might be based on higher order logic provers
be based on higher order logic provers
be based on higher order logic provers or things like SMT
or things like SMT
or things like SMT solvers. And so as I mentioned before,
solvers. And so as I mentioned before,
solvers. And so as I mentioned before, these automated theorem provers really
these automated theorem provers really
these automated theorem provers really struggle with more complex um uh proofs
struggle with more complex um uh proofs
struggle with more complex um uh proofs due to this large search space in their
due to this large search space in their
due to this large search space in their kind of
kind of
kind of formalism. So what we can do to try to
formalism. So what we can do to try to
formalism. So what we can do to try to help with this problem is to solve this
help with this problem is to solve this
help with this problem is to solve this really important problem which is called
really important problem which is called
really important problem which is called premise selection.
premise selection.
premise selection. So basically what you do is you provide
So basically what you do is you provide
So basically what you do is you provide the automated theorem prover with many
the automated theorem prover with many
the automated theorem prover with many different facts. So you can provide it
different facts. So you can provide it
different facts. So you can provide it with you know definitions different
with you know definitions different
with you know definitions different theorems different lemas and then it
theorems different lemas and then it
theorems different lemas and then it goes off and tries to prove the um the
goes off and tries to prove the um the
goes off and tries to prove the um the theorem that you
theorem that you
theorem that you want and if we look at the number of
want and if we look at the number of
want and if we look at the number of premises in say lean's math lab then
premises in say lean's math lab then
premises in say lean's math lab then it's extremely large so it's you know
it's extremely large so it's you know
it's extremely large so it's you know hundreds of thousands of
hundreds of thousands of
hundreds of thousands of premises and so if you just give all of
premises and so if you just give all of
premises and so if you just give all of those to the automated theorem prover it
those to the automated theorem prover it
those to the automated theorem prover it will really struggle because
will really struggle because
will really struggle because um it has this uh really large search
um it has this uh really large search
um it has this uh really large search space. So the basic idea of premise
space. So the basic idea of premise
space. So the basic idea of premise selection is to somehow cut down the
selection is to somehow cut down the
selection is to somehow cut down the number of premises that we give uh and
number of premises that we give uh and
number of premises that we give uh and only provide it ones that are likely to
only provide it ones that are likely to
only provide it ones that are likely to be useful for proving the
be useful for proving the
be useful for proving the theorem. So then we can look at what is
theorem. So then we can look at what is
theorem. So then we can look at what is the typical hammer
the typical hammer
the typical hammer pipeline. So here it is at a kind of
pipeline. So here it is at a kind of
pipeline. So here it is at a kind of high level. Let's say we're in lean.
high level. Let's say we're in lean.
high level. Let's say we're in lean. Then we start off with the thing we want
Then we start off with the thing we want
Then we start off with the thing we want to prove on the
to prove on the
to prove on the left. Then we would pass it to some kind
left. Then we would pass it to some kind
left. Then we would pass it to some kind of premise selection
of premise selection
of premise selection system. Now once we've selected premises
system. Now once we've selected premises
system. Now once we've selected premises like definitions and and theorems, we
like definitions and and theorems, we
like definitions and and theorems, we have to translate it from lean into the
have to translate it from lean into the
have to translate it from lean into the language of the automated theorem
language of the automated theorem
language of the automated theorem prover. Let's say that the automated
prover. Let's say that the automated
prover. Let's say that the automated theorem provers a complete proof. Well,
theorem provers a complete proof. Well,
theorem provers a complete proof. Well, then we have to actually translate it
then we have to actually translate it
then we have to actually translate it back into a lean proof.
back into a lean proof.
back into a lean proof. And so the way that that's done is
And so the way that that's done is
And so the way that that's done is through the step which is called proof
through the step which is called proof
through the step which is called proof reconstruction. So it basically takes
reconstruction. So it basically takes
reconstruction. So it basically takes the output and tries to produce a proof
the output and tries to produce a proof
the output and tries to produce a proof uh in lean. Then as our output we would
uh in lean. Then as our output we would
uh in lean. Then as our output we would see this uh nice proof on the left on
see this uh nice proof on the left on
see this uh nice proof on the left on the right
sorry.
sorry. So amazingly there's been a lot of
So amazingly there's been a lot of
So amazingly there's been a lot of really cool work in the community on
really cool work in the community on
really cool work in the community on these different parts.
these different parts.
these different parts. Usually they're developed somewhat
Usually they're developed somewhat
Usually they're developed somewhat independently of each other, but we have
independently of each other, but we have
independently of each other, but we have this uh translation layer called lean
this uh translation layer called lean
this uh translation layer called lean auto
auto
auto um that can translate from that can help
um that can translate from that can help
um that can translate from that can help translate from lean's dependent type
translate from lean's dependent type
translate from lean's dependent type theory into um the higher order logic.
theory into um the higher order logic.
theory into um the higher order logic. An example automated theorem prover is
An example automated theorem prover is
An example automated theorem prover is called zipper position. And then for
called zipper position. And then for
called zipper position. And then for this proof reconstruction, uh this was
this proof reconstruction, uh this was
this proof reconstruction, uh this was developed by uh Josh Clint and
developed by uh Josh Clint and
developed by uh Josh Clint and collaborators who's part of this lean
collaborators who's part of this lean
collaborators who's part of this lean hammer project. Um and there's a system
hammer project. Um and there's a system
hammer project. Um and there's a system called uh
called uh
called uh duper. So what we're interested in here
duper. So what we're interested in here
duper. So what we're interested in here is two different things. First, we want
is two different things. First, we want
is two different things. First, we want to try to solve this premise selection
to try to solve this premise selection
to try to solve this premise selection problem. And then second, we have to
problem. And then second, we have to
problem. And then second, we have to come up with some way of actually
come up with some way of actually
come up with some way of actually combining these together. When I show it
combining these together. When I show it
combining these together. When I show it on a slide, it looks kind of simple to
on a slide, it looks kind of simple to
on a slide, it looks kind of simple to put them together, but it's actually not
put them together, but it's actually not
put them together, but it's actually not clear what the best way to do this is.
clear what the best way to do this is.
clear what the best way to do this is. And even more, we want to kind of go
And even more, we want to kind of go
And even more, we want to kind of go beyond the standard pipeline, uh, which
beyond the standard pipeline, uh, which
beyond the standard pipeline, uh, which I'll talk about in a
I'll talk about in a
I'll talk about in a bit. So, first let me talk about the
bit. So, first let me talk about the
bit. So, first let me talk about the premise
premise
premise selection. What we do is to frame this
selection. What we do is to frame this
selection. What we do is to frame this as retrieval with a neural language
as retrieval with a neural language
as retrieval with a neural language model.
model.
model. So in particular we have a kind of
So in particular we have a kind of
So in particular we have a kind of standard retrieval setup here. We embed
standard retrieval setup here. We embed
standard retrieval setup here. We embed our input. So this will be the goal that
our input. So this will be the goal that
our input. So this will be the goal that we want to prove and we have a language
we want to prove and we have a language
we want to prove and we have a language model that produces this embedding shown
model that produces this embedding shown
model that produces this embedding shown on the
on the
on the right. Then we embed all of our
right. Then we embed all of our
right. Then we embed all of our potential premises. So this will include
potential premises. So this will include
potential premises. So this will include theorems, definitions, lemas and they
theorems, definitions, lemas and they
theorems, definitions, lemas and they could be from math lab. They could also
could be from math lab. They could also
could be from math lab. They could also be local premises in your project or uh
be local premises in your project or uh
be local premises in your project or uh the in the hypothesis that you're going
the in the hypothesis that you're going
the in the hypothesis that you're going to prove. And with that we get this list
to prove. And with that we get this list
to prove. And with that we get this list of um embeddings shown on the
of um embeddings shown on the
of um embeddings shown on the right. Then to select the premises we
right. Then to select the premises we
right. Then to select the premises we take the dotproduct uh use cosine
take the dotproduct uh use cosine
take the dotproduct uh use cosine similarity to select the set of uh
similarity to select the set of uh
similarity to select the set of uh highest ranked premises.
highest ranked premises.
highest ranked premises. So here we train with this contrastive
So here we train with this contrastive
So here we train with this contrastive loss that is often used to train
loss that is often used to train
loss that is often used to train retrieval models. So it boils down to
retrieval models. So it boils down to
retrieval models. So it boils down to collecting these inputs, the states as
collecting these inputs, the states as
collecting these inputs, the states as well as some positive premises and
well as some positive premises and
well as some positive premises and negative premises.
negative premises.
negative premises. And it turns out that there's actually a
And it turns out that there's actually a
And it turns out that there's actually a lot of nuance in how to do this
lot of nuance in how to do this
lot of nuance in how to do this properly, especially when the output is
properly, especially when the output is
properly, especially when the output is going to be this lean auto uh sorry when
going to be this lean auto uh sorry when
going to be this lean auto uh sorry when the interface is with this lean auto
the interface is with this lean auto
the interface is with this lean auto system in the hammer pipeline. So I
system in the hammer pipeline. So I
system in the hammer pipeline. So I won't go into all the details here and
won't go into all the details here and
won't go into all the details here and when we release the paper it will have
when we release the paper it will have
when we release the paper it will have all the details but even things like how
all the details but even things like how
all the details but even things like how you how and whether you simplify terms
you how and whether you simplify terms
you how and whether you simplify terms um how exactly you choose these positive
um how exactly you choose these positive
um how exactly you choose these positive premises and negative premises turn out
premises and negative premises turn out
premises and negative premises turn out to have a large impact on behavior on on
to have a large impact on behavior on on
to have a large impact on behavior on on the um behavior of the retriever. And so
the um behavior of the retriever. And so
the um behavior of the retriever. And so we'll show in the results in a second
we'll show in the results in a second
we'll show in the results in a second that based on some previous retrievers
that based on some previous retrievers
that based on some previous retrievers that were trained um our system that we
that were trained um our system that we
that were trained um our system that we trained um does a lot better when we put
trained um does a lot better when we put
trained um does a lot better when we put it into this hammer
it into this hammer
it into this hammer pipeline. So then the question is how do
pipeline. So then the question is how do
pipeline. So then the question is how do we combine all of these different
we combine all of these different
we combine all of these different pieces? And so what we did is not just
pieces? And so what we did is not just
pieces? And so what we did is not just have this kind of linear picture that I
have this kind of linear picture that I
have this kind of linear picture that I showed on the previous slide, but we
showed on the previous slide, but we
showed on the previous slide, but we actually incorporate these components
actually incorporate these components
actually incorporate these components into a tree search.
into a tree search.
into a tree search. So there's a really cool tree search
So there's a really cool tree search
So there's a really cool tree search method and it's this kind of symbolic
method and it's this kind of symbolic
method and it's this kind of symbolic tree search called
tree search called
tree search called ASOP and yeah it does this um tree
ASOP and yeah it does this um tree
ASOP and yeah it does this um tree search over different uh tactics or
search over different uh tactics or
search over different uh tactics or steps of the proof. And so what we do is
steps of the proof. And so what we do is
steps of the proof. And so what we do is kind of wire it up so that it can use
kind of wire it up so that it can use
kind of wire it up so that it can use the selected premises to call different
the selected premises to call different
the selected premises to call different tactics in
tactics in
tactics in lean and it can at any time query this
lean and it can at any time query this
lean and it can at any time query this automated theorem prover using the
automated theorem prover using the
automated theorem prover using the selected premises. And so this step will
selected premises. And so this step will
selected premises. And so this step will involve the translation that I mentioned
involve the translation that I mentioned
involve the translation that I mentioned as well as the proof reconstruction.
So now with all of these different parts
So now with all of these different parts that I've described, uh you could say um
that I've described, uh you could say um
that I've described, uh you could say um how how is this actually useful as a
how how is this actually useful as a
how how is this actually useful as a user? Well, um it turns out that we can
user? Well, um it turns out that we can
user? Well, um it turns out that we can wrap this all into one kind of simple
wrap this all into one kind of simple
wrap this all into one kind of simple command. So at any step of a proof, um
command. So at any step of a proof, um
command. So at any step of a proof, um you can just call this hammer tactic and
you can just call this hammer tactic and
you can just call this hammer tactic and then it'll run this tree search that I
then it'll run this tree search that I
then it'll run this tree search that I mentioned. um you know call the external
mentioned. um you know call the external
mentioned. um you know call the external prover and all that and then if it
prover and all that and then if it
prover and all that and then if it succeeds it will display the proof to
succeeds it will display the proof to
succeeds it will display the proof to you uh on the
you uh on the
you uh on the right. And what's cool about this is you
right. And what's cool about this is you
right. And what's cool about this is you could potentially enable this kind of
could potentially enable this kind of
could potentially enable this kind of sketchbased proofing that I was talking
sketchbased proofing that I was talking
sketchbased proofing that I was talking about before. So here I want to show an
about before. So here I want to show an
about before. So here I want to show an actual um demo of the system where we
actual um demo of the system where we
actual um demo of the system where we took a human written proof sketch from
took a human written proof sketch from
took a human written proof sketch from this textbook mathematics and lean uh
this textbook mathematics and lean uh
this textbook mathematics and lean uh and we want to try to fill in the gaps
and we want to try to fill in the gaps
and we want to try to fill in the gaps with the uh hammer
with the uh hammer
with the uh hammer system. So this theorem is the um
system. So this theorem is the um
system. So this theorem is the um irrationality of the square root of two.
irrationality of the square root of two.
irrationality of the square root of two. Um and yeah, sometimes in the formal
Um and yeah, sometimes in the formal
Um and yeah, sometimes in the formal system you'll write it in a slightly um
system you'll write it in a slightly um
system you'll write it in a slightly um different way, but the yeah, the the the
different way, but the yeah, the the the
different way, but the yeah, the the the details are not too important for the
details are not too important for the
details are not too important for the demo, but you can kind of read through
demo, but you can kind of read through
demo, but you can kind of read through uh after if you
uh after if you
uh after if you want. So here we'll um we'll go back
want. So here we'll um we'll go back
want. So here we'll um we'll go back into uh VS code and here is first of all
into uh VS code and here is first of all
into uh VS code and here is first of all the simple um theorem that I showed you
the simple um theorem that I showed you
the simple um theorem that I showed you before.
before.
before. And so what we can do is we can um call
And so what we can do is we can um call
And so what we can do is we can um call this
this
this hammer. And um the first time you run it
hammer. And um the first time you run it
hammer. And um the first time you run it should take um a few seconds. And so
should take um a few seconds. And so
should take um a few seconds. And so what it's done is it's selected the
what it's done is it's selected the
what it's done is it's selected the premises and called the um the the um
premises and called the um the the um
premises and called the um the the um the tree search and all that. And now
the tree search and all that. And now
the tree search and all that. And now you can see that it came back with this
you can see that it came back with this
you can see that it came back with this uh proof this uh theorem or lema.
uh proof this uh theorem or lema.
uh proof this uh theorem or lema. So this one just says that um if 2
So this one just says that um if 2
So this one just says that um if 2 divides m^2 then uh 2 will divide m. So
divides m^2 then uh 2 will divide m. So
divides m^2 then uh 2 will divide m. So it turns out that this one will actually
it turns out that this one will actually
it turns out that this one will actually be useful in this uh irrationality proof
be useful in this uh irrationality proof
be useful in this uh irrationality proof below. So now we can go step by step and
below. So now we can go step by step and
below. So now we can go step by step and try to uh fill in the gaps with the
try to uh fill in the gaps with the
try to uh fill in the gaps with the hammer.
hammer.
hammer. Um, so here it got this one and we can
Um, so here it got this one and we can
Um, so here it got this one and we can just keep
just keep
just keep going. And interestingly up here it
going. And interestingly up here it
going. And interestingly up here it actually used the lema that we just
actually used the lema that we just
actually used the lema that we just proved. So you can see two divide of two
proved. So you can see two divide of two
proved. So you can see two divide of two divide
divide
divide square. Um, and so here it succeeded
square. Um, and so here it succeeded
square. Um, and so here it succeeded again. And I'll just keep going for fun.
So the the idea here is that um by doing
So the the idea here is that um by doing this you don't necessarily have to worry
this you don't necessarily have to worry
this you don't necessarily have to worry about these different details. So here's
about these different details. So here's
about these different details. So here's a kind of interesting one where it's
a kind of interesting one where it's
a kind of interesting one where it's actually calling the automated theorem
actually calling the automated theorem
actually calling the automated theorem prover. Um so you can see all the
prover. Um so you can see all the
prover. Um so you can see all the different facts that are being passed to
different facts that are being passed to
different facts that are being passed to it. And here we could see the call um
it. And here we could see the call um
it. And here we could see the call um the actual call to duper. Uh so duper
the actual call to duper. Uh so duper
the actual call to duper. Uh so duper was this like proof reconstruction
was this like proof reconstruction
was this like proof reconstruction method that I mentioned uh before. So if
method that I mentioned uh before. So if
method that I mentioned uh before. So if you want you could treat this as the
you want you could treat this as the
you want you could treat this as the proof or you can just leave this one in
proof or you can just leave this one in
proof or you can just leave this one in there. Um for this step you actually
there. Um for this step you actually
there. Um for this step you actually have turns out you have to do this one
have turns out you have to do this one
have turns out you have to do this one step of clearing out this
step of clearing out this
step of clearing out this hypothesis. Um, but then you can call it
hypothesis. Um, but then you can call it
hypothesis. Um, but then you can call it the
the
the hammer. And um, just for fun, I'll
hammer. And um, just for fun, I'll
hammer. And um, just for fun, I'll finish off this uh, this proof just to
finish off this uh, this proof just to
finish off this uh, this proof just to show you that it's um, that it's
possible. Okay. And then here's the last
possible. Okay. And then here's the last step and we can call the hammer.
Okay, so now we have a complete proof of
Okay, so now we have a complete proof of the theorem and we started off with
the theorem and we started off with
the theorem and we started off with these kind of highle steps and we're
these kind of highle steps and we're
these kind of highle steps and we're able to um kind of fill in the
able to um kind of fill in the
able to um kind of fill in the gaps. So um again here's the kind of uh
gaps. So um again here's the kind of uh
gaps. So um again here's the kind of uh summary and um then what we could do is
summary and um then what we could do is
summary and um then what we could do is evaluate this with different premise
evaluate this with different premise
evaluate this with different premise selectors uh swapped in. So here's some
selectors uh swapped in. So here's some
selectors uh swapped in. So here's some results on um theorems that we held out
results on um theorems that we held out
results on um theorems that we held out from math lab as a kind of test set and
from math lab as a kind of test set and
from math lab as a kind of test set and we just run the hammer at the first step
we just run the hammer at the first step
we just run the hammer at the first step of the proof. So on the left here you
of the proof. So on the left here you
of the proof. So on the left here you could see what happens if you don't have
could see what happens if you don't have
could see what happens if you don't have the premise selection.
the premise selection.
the premise selection. Um then here is using a um retriever
Um then here is using a um retriever
Um then here is using a um retriever that was uh from prior work. What we did
that was uh from prior work. What we did
that was uh from prior work. What we did is we retrained it on the exact same um
is we retrained it on the exact same um
is we retrained it on the exact same um snapshot of Mathlib. So it had kind of
snapshot of Mathlib. So it had kind of
snapshot of Mathlib. So it had kind of up-to-date data and it's partially
up-to-date data and it's partially
up-to-date data and it's partially showing that like the specific decisions
showing that like the specific decisions
showing that like the specific decisions that we make in training our retriever
that we make in training our retriever
that we make in training our retriever um were really important for
um were really important for
um were really important for performance. Interestingly, there's a
performance. Interestingly, there's a
performance. Interestingly, there's a symbolic premise selection system. I
symbolic premise selection system. I
symbolic premise selection system. I believe it's based on the one that was
believe it's based on the one that was
believe it's based on the one that was in the Isabel sledgehammer. Um, so Kim
in the Isabel sledgehammer. Um, so Kim
in the Isabel sledgehammer. Um, so Kim Morrison from the lean community um
Morrison from the lean community um
Morrison from the lean community um reimplemented it in lean and you can see
reimplemented it in lean and you can see
reimplemented it in lean and you can see that it actually does pretty um pretty
that it actually does pretty um pretty
that it actually does pretty um pretty decently when it's in our hammer
decently when it's in our hammer
decently when it's in our hammer pipeline. Here is the lean hammer
pipeline. Here is the lean hammer
pipeline. Here is the lean hammer retriever um as the fourth bar with the
retriever um as the fourth bar with the
retriever um as the fourth bar with the kind of diagonal lines. And then
kind of diagonal lines. And then
kind of diagonal lines. And then interestingly it ends up being
interestingly it ends up being
interestingly it ends up being complimentary to the symbolic um meo
complimentary to the symbolic um meo
complimentary to the symbolic um meo retriever. So you could see with these
retriever. So you could see with these
retriever. So you could see with these kind of cross-hatch lines, uh, you get a
kind of cross-hatch lines, uh, you get a
kind of cross-hatch lines, uh, you get a performance boost if you just take the
performance boost if you just take the
performance boost if you just take the union of
union of
union of premises. And then in absolute terms,
premises. And then in absolute terms,
premises. And then in absolute terms, it's starting to get pretty good. So all
it's starting to get pretty good. So all
it's starting to get pretty good. So all the way on the right is the performance
the way on the right is the performance
the way on the right is the performance that we get if we just use the ground
that we get if we just use the ground
that we get if we just use the ground truth premises that um occur in the
truth premises that um occur in the
truth premises that um occur in the human proof. And you can see that the
human proof. And you can see that the
human proof. And you can see that the performance is starting to approach um
performance is starting to approach um
performance is starting to approach um the performance that we get if we use
those. Um so to recap, I talked about
those. Um so to recap, I talked about two different approaches for um
two different approaches for um
two different approaches for um combining informal and formal provers or
combining informal and formal provers or
combining informal and formal provers or even formal informal proofs. Um I talked
even formal informal proofs. Um I talked
even formal informal proofs. Um I talked about draft sketch proof which involves
about draft sketch proof which involves
about draft sketch proof which involves drafting an informal proof um generating
drafting an informal proof um generating
drafting an informal proof um generating a formal sketch and then filling in the
a formal sketch and then filling in the
a formal sketch and then filling in the low-level
low-level
low-level details. And I talked about lean hammer
details. And I talked about lean hammer
details. And I talked about lean hammer which is trying to bring this kind of
which is trying to bring this kind of
which is trying to bring this kind of paradigm to lean or make it easier. So
paradigm to lean or make it easier. So
paradigm to lean or make it easier. So in particular we try to build this
in particular we try to build this
in particular we try to build this hammer and it involves this neural
hammer and it involves this neural
hammer and it involves this neural premise selection and a tree search and
premise selection and a tree search and
premise selection and a tree search and calling out to the automated theorem
prover and one uh interesting takeaway
prover and one uh interesting takeaway from this is I didn't go into detail of
from this is I didn't go into detail of
from this is I didn't go into detail of the model that we trained but the
the model that we trained but the
the model that we trained but the largest model that we trained was just a
largest model that we trained was just a
largest model that we trained was just a 100 million parameter retriever so very
100 million parameter retriever so very
100 million parameter retriever so very small and as you maybe saw in the demo
small and as you maybe saw in the demo
small and as you maybe saw in the demo you can get some pretty non-trivial
you can get some pretty non-trivial
you can get some pretty non-trivial behavior um or performance from
behavior um or performance from
behavior um or performance from integrating it in. So it's kind of
integrating it in. So it's kind of
integrating it in. So it's kind of exciting because yeah in these cases
exciting because yeah in these cases
exciting because yeah in these cases even these fairly small by today's
even these fairly small by today's
even these fairly small by today's standards neural networks can be uh
standards neural networks can be uh
standards neural networks can be uh fairly powerful.
fairly powerful.
fairly powerful. So in the last part of the talk I want
So in the last part of the talk I want
So in the last part of the talk I want to talk about um trying to use AI or
to talk about um trying to use AI or
to talk about um trying to use AI or techniques that I've talked about to
techniques that I've talked about to
techniques that I've talked about to actually assist in research level
actually assist in research level
actually assist in research level mathematics. So, not just prove the um
mathematics. So, not just prove the um
mathematics. So, not just prove the um IMO problems, but try to help out in
IMO problems, but try to help out in
IMO problems, but try to help out in these more complex pro uh projects that
these more complex pro uh projects that
these more complex pro uh projects that um mathematicians or if you're a kind of
um mathematicians or if you're a kind of
um mathematicians or if you're a kind of like lean um hobbyist or interested in
like lean um hobbyist or interested in
like lean um hobbyist or interested in formalizing something
formalizing something
formalizing something difficult. So, what does it actually
difficult. So, what does it actually
difficult. So, what does it actually look like to formalize research level
look like to formalize research level
look like to formalize research level math? Well, here we can look at this
math? Well, here we can look at this
math? Well, here we can look at this blog post that was written by Terrence
blog post that was written by Terrence
blog post that was written by Terrence Tao and he kind of breaks down the steps
Tao and he kind of breaks down the steps
Tao and he kind of breaks down the steps that were involved in formalizing a
that were involved in formalizing a
that were involved in formalizing a proof from this paper which is shown on
proof from this paper which is shown on
proof from this paper which is shown on the
the
the left. So again the goal was to take one
left. So again the goal was to take one
left. So again the goal was to take one of the main theorems from the paper and
of the main theorems from the paper and
of the main theorems from the paper and then try to write it in lean and come up
then try to write it in lean and come up
then try to write it in lean and come up with a formal proof. And the first step
with a formal proof. And the first step
with a formal proof. And the first step is to write what is called a blueprint.
is to write what is called a blueprint.
is to write what is called a blueprint. So here you kind of go step by step and
So here you kind of go step by step and
So here you kind of go step by step and think about how would this proof
think about how would this proof
think about how would this proof decompose into different definitions
decompose into different definitions
decompose into different definitions into different lemmas and ultimately uh
into different lemmas and ultimately uh
into different lemmas and ultimately uh we can come up with the kind of final
we can come up with the kind of final
we can come up with the kind of final theorem and proof that we care about.
theorem and proof that we care about.
theorem and proof that we care about. And as you can see here on the top it's
And as you can see here on the top it's
And as you can see here on the top it's showing a kind of dependency graph of
showing a kind of dependency graph of
showing a kind of dependency graph of all of these theorems and all of these
all of these theorems and all of these
all of these theorems and all of these definitions. So it gets fairly complex
definitions. So it gets fairly complex
definitions. So it gets fairly complex and at the very bottom you have the
and at the very bottom you have the
and at the very bottom you have the final theorem and final
final theorem and final
final theorem and final proof and so interestingly here
proof and so interestingly here
proof and so interestingly here everything is still written in informal
everything is still written in informal
everything is still written in informal language. So you could see here the
language. So you could see here the
language. So you could see here the theorem and the proof uh just written in
theorem and the proof uh just written in
theorem and the proof uh just written in latte and then you try to think about
latte and then you try to think about
latte and then you try to think about okay how do we actually realize this in
okay how do we actually realize this in
okay how do we actually realize this in lean and so what it comes down to is a
lean and so what it comes down to is a
lean and so what it comes down to is a large set of these formal definitions
large set of these formal definitions
large set of these formal definitions and formal lemas and and formal theorems
and formal lemas and and formal theorems
and formal lemas and and formal theorems and then ultimately you're able to kind
and then ultimately you're able to kind
and then ultimately you're able to kind of state your final theorem and write
of state your final theorem and write
of state your final theorem and write the proof of
the proof of
the proof of it. So at the end you have this proof
it. So at the end you have this proof
it. So at the end you have this proof and this theorem that are really
and this theorem that are really
and this theorem that are really dependent on this kind of graph of
dependent on this kind of graph of
dependent on this kind of graph of things that I showed
things that I showed
things that I showed you. So a question is like at what point
you. So a question is like at what point
you. So a question is like at what point of this procedure could AI
of this procedure could AI
of this procedure could AI help? So maybe at least for now we don't
help? So maybe at least for now we don't
help? So maybe at least for now we don't have it do this whole pipeline end to
have it do this whole pipeline end to
have it do this whole pipeline end to end but we could think about like what
end but we could think about like what
end but we could think about like what is the simplest thing that we could have
is the simplest thing that we could have
is the simplest thing that we could have it do and that we could have kind of uh
it do and that we could have kind of uh
it do and that we could have kind of uh trust. So one thing you could do is you
trust. So one thing you could do is you
trust. So one thing you could do is you could look at this blueprint and look at
could look at this blueprint and look at
could look at this blueprint and look at just one of these kind of theorems or
just one of these kind of theorems or
just one of these kind of theorems or lemos that is um kind of necessary for
lemos that is um kind of necessary for
lemos that is um kind of necessary for the proof but is just one part of it.
the proof but is just one part of it.
the proof but is just one part of it. So here's an example where we have this
So here's an example where we have this
So here's an example where we have this lema which occurs somewhere in here and
lema which occurs somewhere in here and
lema which occurs somewhere in here and if we give this to a language model and
if we give this to a language model and
if we give this to a language model and it produces a proof then again we can
it produces a proof then again we can
it produces a proof then again we can kind of trust the output because lean
kind of trust the output because lean
kind of trust the output because lean has checked it and in some sense it's
has checked it and in some sense it's
has checked it and in some sense it's helped the development because then the
helped the development because then the
helped the development because then the um human proof writer doesn't have to
um human proof writer doesn't have to
um human proof writer doesn't have to kind of go go through this
kind of go go through this
kind of go go through this step. So in order to do this um we
step. So in order to do this um we
step. So in order to do this um we really have to overcome two uh at least
really have to overcome two uh at least
really have to overcome two uh at least two different gaps that um that
two different gaps that um that
two different gaps that um that occur. The first I'll call the
occur. The first I'll call the
occur. The first I'll call the accessibility gap and this is just the
accessibility gap and this is just the
accessibility gap and this is just the kind of simple observation that a lot of
kind of simple observation that a lot of
kind of simple observation that a lot of times these methods are developed but
times these methods are developed but
times these methods are developed but then they're actually hard to integrate
then they're actually hard to integrate
then they're actually hard to integrate into actual tools. So for example, the
into actual tools. So for example, the
into actual tools. So for example, the system might be very capable, but it
system might be very capable, but it
system might be very capable, but it might not be open source or the results
might not be open source or the results
might not be open source or the results might be very impressive, but then
might be very impressive, but then
might be very impressive, but then they're actually very expensive or
they're actually very expensive or
they're actually very expensive or costly to run. And so when you think
costly to run. And so when you think
costly to run. And so when you think about this kind of practical setting, it
about this kind of practical setting, it
about this kind of practical setting, it adds constraints onto the methods that
adds constraints onto the methods that
adds constraints onto the methods that you have to develop.
you have to develop.
you have to develop. But luckily we actually do have some
But luckily we actually do have some
But luckily we actually do have some tools already available that could
tools already available that could
tools already available that could potentially be useful for these kind of
potentially be useful for these kind of
potentially be useful for these kind of simple
simple
simple gaps. Um so we developed one of them
gaps. Um so we developed one of them
gaps. Um so we developed one of them called LLM lean and you could go
called LLM lean and you could go
called LLM lean and you could go download it and and use it um right now
download it and and use it um right now
download it and and use it um right now if you want. And so the basic idea is to
if you want. And so the basic idea is to
if you want. And so the basic idea is to just create this interface between lean
just create this interface between lean
just create this interface between lean and some language model.
and some language model.
and some language model. So what it does is it gives you these
So what it does is it gives you these
So what it does is it gives you these different uh commands or tactics. Uh
different uh commands or tactics. Uh
different uh commands or tactics. Uh like this one queries a language model
like this one queries a language model
like this one queries a language model to try to produce the next step of the
to try to produce the next step of the
to try to produce the next step of the proof. And then we can actually check
proof. And then we can actually check
proof. And then we can actually check the outputs of the model. So we could
the outputs of the model. So we could
the outputs of the model. So we could discard the incorrect ones and just
discard the incorrect ones and just
discard the incorrect ones and just display ones that kind of finish the
display ones that kind of finish the
display ones that kind of finish the proof. Those are shown in green or blue
proof. Those are shown in green or blue
proof. Those are shown in green or blue ones are ones that kind of don't give an
ones are ones that kind of don't give an
ones are ones that kind of don't give an error but don't necessarily uh finish
error but don't necessarily uh finish
error but don't necessarily uh finish the proof.
the proof.
the proof. And um in particular you can uh even
And um in particular you can uh even
And um in particular you can uh even nowadays have a model running on your
nowadays have a model running on your
nowadays have a model running on your laptop. So there's these different
laptop. So there's these different
laptop. So there's these different libraries that have been developed uh
libraries that have been developed uh
libraries that have been developed uh like Olama or LM Studio and you could
like Olama or LM Studio and you could
like Olama or LM Studio and you could basically host the language model on
basically host the language model on
basically host the language model on your laptop and then use LLM lean to
your laptop and then use LLM lean to
your laptop and then use LLM lean to communicate with
communicate with
communicate with it. Similarly you can have it
it. Similarly you can have it
it. Similarly you can have it communicate with um some API. So it
communicate with um some API. So it
communicate with um some API. So it could be open AAI, it could be claude,
could be open AAI, it could be claude,
could be open AAI, it could be claude, Gemini, um,
Gemini, um,
Gemini, um, together.AI. And so now you can actually
together.AI. And so now you can actually
together.AI. And so now you can actually try to use these models to give you
try to use these models to give you
try to use these models to give you suggestions that are checked and
suggestions that are checked and
suggestions that are checked and lean. So as the last demo, I wanted to
lean. So as the last demo, I wanted to
lean. So as the last demo, I wanted to um just uh show you this
um just uh show you this
um just uh show you this um and so let's look for the other
um and so let's look for the other
um and so let's look for the other window.
window.
window. Okay, so let's go back to this really
Okay, so let's go back to this really
Okay, so let's go back to this really simple theorem that I showed at the
simple theorem that I showed at the
simple theorem that I showed at the beginning of the
beginning of the
beginning of the talk. Um, and you probably you might
talk. Um, and you probably you might
talk. Um, and you probably you might have noticed that I imported this lm
have noticed that I imported this lm
have noticed that I imported this lm lean here. And so now we could call this
lean here. And so now we could call this
lean here. And so now we could call this lm step uh command that I
lm step uh command that I
lm step uh command that I showed and actually comes up with this
showed and actually comes up with this
showed and actually comes up with this uh intro command that I showed you at
uh intro command that I showed you at
uh intro command that I showed you at the beginning of the
the beginning of the
the beginning of the talk. Then we could call it um again
talk. Then we could call it um again
talk. Then we could call it um again And in this case it um yeah was able to
And in this case it um yeah was able to
And in this case it um yeah was able to finish the
finish the
finish the proof. Um so another thing you can do is
proof. Um so another thing you can do is
proof. Um so another thing you can do is you can you could say like try to just
you can you could say like try to just
you can you could say like try to just do this exact command. So try to prove
do this exact command. So try to prove
do this exact command. So try to prove it in one step. Um it actually came up
it in one step. Um it actually came up
it in one step. Um it actually came up with this
with this
with this um bit more clever kind of one-step uh
um bit more clever kind of one-step uh
um bit more clever kind of one-step uh proof. Uh there's another command that
proof. Uh there's another command that
proof. Uh there's another command that just tries to prove it um in end to end
just tries to prove it um in end to end
just tries to prove it um in end to end uh pro like fully prove it instead of
uh pro like fully prove it instead of
uh pro like fully prove it instead of just predicting the next
just predicting the next
just predicting the next step.
step.
step. Um so here the model comes up with um
Um so here the model comes up with um
Um so here the model comes up with um yeah multiple potential uh proofs and
yeah multiple potential uh proofs and
yeah multiple potential uh proofs and you can see they're a bit different
you can see they're a bit different
you can see they're a bit different style maybe um bit
style maybe um bit
style maybe um bit longer. So you can also do other like
longer. So you can also do other like
longer. So you can also do other like fun things like um shorten this
fun things like um shorten this
fun things like um shorten this proof and put it as
proof and put it as
proof and put it as a comment and then call the
lmqd. So let's see what it does. And
lmqd. So let's see what it does. And yeah, so now it gives us some options
yeah, so now it gives us some options
yeah, so now it gives us some options that are shorter. Actually, this is
that are shorter. Actually, this is
that are shorter. Actually, this is pretty short. You could just prove it in
pretty short. You could just prove it in
pretty short. You could just prove it in kind of one call.
kind of one call.
kind of one call. Um so yeah this is a tool that you could
Um so yeah this is a tool that you could
Um so yeah this is a tool that you could use um today you just need to uh you
use um today you just need to uh you
use um today you just need to uh you know have a language model API um and
know have a language model API um and
know have a language model API um and then um yeah you can import it into uh
then um yeah you can import it into uh
then um yeah you can import it into uh to a lean
to a lean
to a lean project. Um so interestingly
project. Um so interestingly
project. Um so interestingly um let's see here the methods are still
um let's see here the methods are still
um let's see here the methods are still bottlenecked obviously by how good the
bottlenecked obviously by how good the
bottlenecked obviously by how good the model is at uh proving theorems. Um but
model is at uh proving theorems. Um but
model is at uh proving theorems. Um but like even now um I kind of went through
like even now um I kind of went through
like even now um I kind of went through Terrence TA's project this PFR project
Terrence TA's project this PFR project
Terrence TA's project this PFR project and just picked a file and um yeah this
and just picked a file and um yeah this
and just picked a file and um yeah this one was actually able to fill in some of
one was actually able to fill in some of
one was actually able to fill in some of these uh um yeah small small lemas. This
these uh um yeah small small lemas. This
these uh um yeah small small lemas. This was actually the example that I showed
was actually the example that I showed
was actually the example that I showed you before uh on the previous slide.
So another thing is I mentioned that the
So another thing is I mentioned that the models right now are the kind of
models right now are the kind of
models right now are the kind of bottleneck right we have the interface
bottleneck right we have the interface
bottleneck right we have the interface set up and so now it just comes down to
set up and so now it just comes down to
set up and so now it just comes down to whether the model can complete um
whether the model can complete um
whether the model can complete um theorems that occur in these kind of
theorems that occur in these kind of
theorems that occur in these kind of kinds of
kinds of
kinds of projects. So this leads to a second kind
projects. So this leads to a second kind
projects. So this leads to a second kind of gap which is the gap in the way that
of gap which is the gap in the way that
of gap which is the gap in the way that we benchmark these theorem proving
we benchmark these theorem proving
we benchmark these theorem proving models. So largely these models are
models. So largely these models are
models. So largely these models are benchmarked on their ability to prove
benchmarked on their ability to prove
benchmarked on their ability to prove these math competition problems like
these math competition problems like
these math competition problems like ones from the
ones from the
ones from the IMO. And what these problems have is
IMO. And what these problems have is
IMO. And what these problems have is they're fairly self-contained. Um so you
they're fairly self-contained. Um so you
they're fairly self-contained. Um so you can usually state the problem in just
can usually state the problem in just
can usually state the problem in just like one line of code. And then they're
like one line of code. And then they're
like one line of code. And then they're kind of designed to somewhat use
kind of designed to somewhat use
kind of designed to somewhat use standard results. Um so there's a kind
standard results. Um so there's a kind
standard results. Um so there's a kind of standard set and you know a lot of
of standard set and you know a lot of
of standard set and you know a lot of them have been implemented in math lib
them have been implemented in math lib
them have been implemented in math lib and then constructing the proof is very
and then constructing the proof is very
and then constructing the proof is very difficult. It requires a lot of
difficult. It requires a lot of
difficult. It requires a lot of creativity but it's kind of relying on
creativity but it's kind of relying on
creativity but it's kind of relying on these uh standard
these uh standard
these uh standard results. If we compare that to this
results. If we compare that to this
results. If we compare that to this project that I've been telling you
project that I've been telling you
project that I've been telling you about, these have these complex
about, these have these complex
about, these have these complex dependencies from throughout the
dependencies from throughout the
dependencies from throughout the project. So in particular, um this
project. So in particular, um this
project. So in particular, um this theorem to even state it or to prove it,
theorem to even state it or to prove it,
theorem to even state it or to prove it, it might actually rely on these brand
it might actually rely on these brand
it might actually rely on these brand new definitions and brand new lemmas
new definitions and brand new lemmas
new definitions and brand new lemmas that have been created for the project.
that have been created for the project.
that have been created for the project. And so unless we like continually train
And so unless we like continually train
And so unless we like continually train the model on all of the current
the model on all of the current
the model on all of the current projects, it really has to learn to
projects, it really has to learn to
projects, it really has to learn to prove theorems in this kind of context
prove theorems in this kind of context
prove theorems in this kind of context dependent setting that I'm showing on
dependent setting that I'm showing on
dependent setting that I'm showing on the
the
the right. So this leads to our um new
right. So this leads to our um new
right. So this leads to our um new benchmark called mini CTX or mini
benchmark called mini CTX or mini
benchmark called mini CTX or mini context. And we'll also be presenting
context. And we'll also be presenting
context. And we'll also be presenting this at iClar as an oral presentation.
this at iClar as an oral presentation.
this at iClar as an oral presentation. So here what we do is we made this
So here what we do is we made this
So here what we do is we made this observation that I just told you about
observation that I just told you about
observation that I just told you about that when we look at these real these
that when we look at these real these
that when we look at these real these kind of research level or actual
kind of research level or actual
kind of research level or actual formalizations that people do in lean
formalizations that people do in lean
formalizations that people do in lean they are really in this context
they are really in this context
they are really in this context dependent setting where you want to
dependent setting where you want to
dependent setting where you want to prove a theorem and it depends on like a
prove a theorem and it depends on like a
prove a theorem and it depends on like a whole repository of code new definitions
whole repository of code new definitions
whole repository of code new definitions or new auxiliary
or new auxiliary
or new auxiliary lemos. So the idea of the benchmark is
lemos. So the idea of the benchmark is
lemos. So the idea of the benchmark is to test models on actual real lean
to test models on actual real lean
to test models on actual real lean projects. So in particular we choose
projects. So in particular we choose
projects. So in particular we choose some date cutoff and then we look at a
some date cutoff and then we look at a
some date cutoff and then we look at a project like math lab and we can take
project like math lab and we can take
project like math lab and we can take all of the theorems that were developed
all of the theorems that were developed
all of the theorems that were developed after that
after that
after that date. Similarly we can look at when a
date. Similarly we can look at when a
date. Similarly we can look at when a project was created and take theorems um
project was created and take theorems um
project was created and take theorems um and kind of contexts from those
and kind of contexts from those
and kind of contexts from those different projects. So this PFR project
different projects. So this PFR project
different projects. So this PFR project by um Terrence Town and collaborators
by um Terrence Town and collaborators
by um Terrence Town and collaborators that I've been telling you about is like
that I've been telling you about is like
that I've been telling you about is like one of the projects that was in the
one of the projects that was in the
one of the projects that was in the first version of this uh
first version of this uh
first version of this uh benchmark. Then the idea is we also make
benchmark. Then the idea is we also make
benchmark. Then the idea is we also make tools so that you can automatically
tools so that you can automatically
tools so that you can automatically extract benchmark problems from these
extract benchmark problems from these
extract benchmark problems from these projects. So what you can do is update
projects. So what you can do is update
projects. So what you can do is update the benchmark to kind of stay ahead of
the benchmark to kind of stay ahead of
the benchmark to kind of stay ahead of the training cutoffs for these language
the training cutoffs for these language
the training cutoffs for these language models. So we've actually already
models. So we've actually already
models. So we've actually already released a mini CTX uh version two and
released a mini CTX uh version two and
released a mini CTX uh version two and it has kind of more recent pro um lean
it has kind of more recent pro um lean
it has kind of more recent pro um lean projects that have been developed like
projects that have been developed like
projects that have been developed like in the past couple of months.
in the past couple of months.
in the past couple of months. So here we have two different types of
So here we have two different types of
So here we have two different types of contexts and um these are basically like
contexts and um these are basically like
contexts and um these are basically like what dependencies are needed to prove a
what dependencies are needed to prove a
what dependencies are needed to prove a theorem and what we do is we build
theorem and what we do is we build
theorem and what we do is we build tooling to automatically extract um
tooling to automatically extract um
tooling to automatically extract um things like
things like
things like dependencies and um so and we can look
dependencies and um so and we can look
dependencies and um so and we can look at like does a theorem depend on things
at like does a theorem depend on things
at like does a theorem depend on things just in the current file or does it
just in the current file or does it
just in the current file or does it depend on things across multiple files.
depend on things across multiple files.
depend on things across multiple files. And then we can also get things like you
And then we can also get things like you
And then we can also get things like you know what are the set of available
know what are the set of available
know what are the set of available premises when you're going to prove this
premises when you're going to prove this
premises when you're going to prove this theorem. So kind of very realistic
theorem. So kind of very realistic
theorem. So kind of very realistic setting. So in particular let's look at
setting. So in particular let's look at
setting. So in particular let's look at two different settings. One setting is
two different settings. One setting is
two different settings. One setting is where all of the dependencies just
where all of the dependencies just
where all of the dependencies just appear in the current file. Uh and then
appear in the current file. Uh and then
appear in the current file. Uh and then the other is when the dependencies can
the other is when the dependencies can
the other is when the dependencies can span multiple files.
span multiple files.
span multiple files. So the first thing we want to do is
So the first thing we want to do is
So the first thing we want to do is actually demonstrate that this context
actually demonstrate that this context
actually demonstrate that this context actually
actually
actually matters. So again I've told you about
matters. So again I've told you about
matters. So again I've told you about this really common way of training uh
this really common way of training uh
this really common way of training uh theorem provers which is by just giving
theorem provers which is by just giving
theorem provers which is by just giving them the proof state and then having
them the proof state and then having
them the proof state and then having them produce a next step or having them
them produce a next step or having them
them produce a next step or having them kind of produce thoughts if you want.
kind of produce thoughts if you want.
kind of produce thoughts if you want. So here what we did is um develop this
So here what we did is um develop this
So here what we did is um develop this simple baseline method which
simple baseline method which
simple baseline method which additionally gives the model all of the
additionally gives the model all of the
additionally gives the model all of the code in the file uh so far. So this can
code in the file uh so far. So this can
code in the file uh so far. So this can include like new definitions uh new
include like new definitions uh new
include like new definitions uh new lemas even like new notation or natural
lemas even like new notation or natural
lemas even like new notation or natural language comments and we wanted to see
language comments and we wanted to see
language comments and we wanted to see how this compared to just taking in the
how this compared to just taking in the
how this compared to just taking in the proof state.
proof state.
proof state. So interestingly, if you look at a
So interestingly, if you look at a
So interestingly, if you look at a competition problem data set like mini
competition problem data set like mini
competition problem data set like mini F2F, it actually really doesn't matter.
F2F, it actually really doesn't matter.
F2F, it actually really doesn't matter. You can do pretty similarly whether you
You can do pretty similarly whether you
You can do pretty similarly whether you take in additional context. It would
take in additional context. It would
take in additional context. It would just be like the import statements for
just be like the import statements for
just be like the import statements for mini F2F um or if you just take the
mini F2F um or if you just take the
mini F2F um or if you just take the proof state. So this might be one reason
proof state. So this might be one reason
proof state. So this might be one reason why a lot of these state-of-the-art
why a lot of these state-of-the-art
why a lot of these state-of-the-art theorem proving methods don't really um
theorem proving methods don't really um
theorem proving methods don't really um deal with or support any kind of
deal with or support any kind of
deal with or support any kind of external
external
external context. However, when we evaluate them
context. However, when we evaluate them
context. However, when we evaluate them on um our benchmark mini CTX which has
on um our benchmark mini CTX which has
on um our benchmark mini CTX which has the um theorems from real real world
the um theorems from real real world
the um theorems from real real world projects, we can see this dramatic gap
projects, we can see this dramatic gap
projects, we can see this dramatic gap in the
in the
in the performance. And the reason is pretty
performance. And the reason is pretty
performance. And the reason is pretty obvious if you just look at a lean file.
obvious if you just look at a lean file.
obvious if you just look at a lean file. It's because in these real projects
It's because in these real projects
It's because in these real projects you're defining these kind of new
you're defining these kind of new
you're defining these kind of new definitions and new lemmos like I
definitions and new lemmos like I
definitions and new lemmos like I discussed. Interestingly, um you can
discussed. Interestingly, um you can
discussed. Interestingly, um you can also do this uh premise selection and
also do this uh premise selection and
also do this uh premise selection and kind of give the language model the
kind of give the language model the
kind of give the language model the premises. Um and you can see variations
premises. Um and you can see variations
premises. Um and you can see variations on based on whether the theorem requires
on based on whether the theorem requires
on based on whether the theorem requires just infile information or out of file
just infile information or out of file
just infile information or out of file information.
information.
information. Um so all the way on the left we have
Um so all the way on the left we have
Um so all the way on the left we have theorems with um very low
theorems with um very low
theorems with um very low dependencies. The first set of bar
dependencies. The first set of bar
dependencies. The first set of bar graphs shows um high dependencies on
graphs shows um high dependencies on
graphs shows um high dependencies on infile premises. And so here you could
infile premises. And so here you could
infile premises. And so here you could see that you do pretty well by just
see that you do pretty well by just
see that you do pretty well by just giving the language model all the code
giving the language model all the code
giving the language model all the code in the current file. And then in the
in the current file. And then in the
in the current file. And then in the third set of bar graphs you see what
third set of bar graphs you see what
third set of bar graphs you see what happens when we have these cross file
happens when we have these cross file
happens when we have these cross file dependencies. And you can see that
dependencies. And you can see that
dependencies. And you can see that adding in this premise selection uh
adding in this premise selection uh
adding in this premise selection uh leads to some
leads to some
leads to some improvement. So here we are using a um
improvement. So here we are using a um
improvement. So here we are using a um an older premise selector system. So
an older premise selector system. So
an older premise selector system. So we're excited about like integrating our
we're excited about like integrating our
we're excited about like integrating our uh lean hammer into this for addressing
uh lean hammer into this for addressing
uh lean hammer into this for addressing the cross file dependencies. Uh and in
the cross file dependencies. Uh and in
the cross file dependencies. Uh and in general there's a kind of wide space of
general there's a kind of wide space of
general there's a kind of wide space of methods that could be developed um for
methods that could be developed um for
methods that could be developed um for this setting.
this setting.
this setting. Um, so I should also mention that we um
Um, so I should also mention that we um
Um, so I should also mention that we um provide the model with this file tuning.
provide the model with this file tuning.
provide the model with this file tuning. So it's trained to take in the file
So it's trained to take in the file
So it's trained to take in the file context um through O Lama. So you can
context um through O Lama. So you can
context um through O Lama. So you can like download it, run it on your laptop
like download it, run it on your laptop
like download it, run it on your laptop and use it inside of
and use it inside of
and use it inside of Lean. Um, and then all of the methods
Lean. Um, and then all of the methods
Lean. Um, and then all of the methods that are in LLM lean that are calling
that are in LLM lean that are calling
that are in LLM lean that are calling the proprietary language models or the
the proprietary language models or the
the proprietary language models or the API based ones. Um, they'll actually
API based ones. Um, they'll actually
API based ones. Um, they'll actually prompt the model with all of the code in
prompt the model with all of the code in
prompt the model with all of the code in the current
the current
the current file. Um, and then as I mentioned
file. Um, and then as I mentioned
file. Um, and then as I mentioned everything from the project is open
everything from the project is open
everything from the project is open source. So the data, the models, um our
source. So the data, the models, um our
source. So the data, the models, um our data extraction tool and uh even the um
data extraction tool and uh even the um
data extraction tool and uh even the um evaluation code which is like a wrapper
evaluation code which is like a wrapper
evaluation code which is like a wrapper of the lean uh ripple and so you can
of the lean uh ripple and so you can
of the lean uh ripple and so you can check out those resources um
online. Um so as I mentioned in this
online. Um so as I mentioned in this third part if we look at um these kind
third part if we look at um these kind
third part if we look at um these kind of real lean projects or what it would
of real lean projects or what it would
of real lean projects or what it would take to formalize research level math it
take to formalize research level math it
take to formalize research level math it opens up some unique challenges. Uh
opens up some unique challenges. Uh
opens up some unique challenges. Uh these aren't the only challenges of
these aren't the only challenges of
these aren't the only challenges of course but uh two that are really
course but uh two that are really
course but uh two that are really present in the kind of research
present in the kind of research
present in the kind of research community right now. One is that we
community right now. One is that we
community right now. One is that we still have a gap between the AI advances
still have a gap between the AI advances
still have a gap between the AI advances and tools that people can use. And then
and tools that people can use. And then
and tools that people can use. And then second, the benchmarks don't always
second, the benchmarks don't always
second, the benchmarks don't always reflect all of the capabilities that are
reflect all of the capabilities that are
reflect all of the capabilities that are required to do this real world
required to do this real world
required to do this real world formalization. And so this is very much
formalization. And so this is very much
formalization. And so this is very much an open research direction. And as I
an open research direction. And as I
an open research direction. And as I mentioned, this benchmark is kind of the
mentioned, this benchmark is kind of the
mentioned, this benchmark is kind of the the first
the first
the first step. So in summary, in this talk, I
step. So in summary, in this talk, I
step. So in summary, in this talk, I talked about three different ways to try
talked about three different ways to try
talked about three different ways to try to bridge informal and formal
to bridge informal and formal
to bridge informal and formal mathematical reasoning. I talked about
mathematical reasoning. I talked about
mathematical reasoning. I talked about incorporating informal thoughts by
incorporating informal thoughts by
incorporating informal thoughts by training models to think
training models to think
training models to think informally. I talked about incorporating
informally. I talked about incorporating
informally. I talked about incorporating informal provers or informal uh proofs
informal provers or informal uh proofs
informal provers or informal uh proofs through methods that sketch proofs and
through methods that sketch proofs and
through methods that sketch proofs and try to fill in the gaps. And then
try to fill in the gaps. And then
try to fill in the gaps. And then towards the end I talked about trying to
towards the end I talked about trying to
towards the end I talked about trying to take say a research paper and look at
take say a research paper and look at
take say a research paper and look at what is involved in producing a formal
what is involved in producing a formal
what is involved in producing a formal version of it and looking at what are
version of it and looking at what are
version of it and looking at what are some initial ways where AI can help in
some initial ways where AI can help in
some initial ways where AI can help in the
the
the process. And so with that that is all I
process. And so with that that is all I
process. And so with that that is all I have for today's talk. And I'd like to
have for today's talk. And I'd like to
have for today's talk. And I'd like to thank um all of the amazing
thank um all of the amazing
thank um all of the amazing collaborators on these various works. Um
collaborators on these various works. Um
collaborators on these various works. Um they're listed here. And again, my name
they're listed here. And again, my name
they're listed here. And again, my name is uh Sean and I have my email address
is uh Sean and I have my email address
is uh Sean and I have my email address here.